<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss version='2.0' xmlns:atom='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'>
<channel>
<atom:link href='https://ddft.wiki/' rel='self' type='application/rss+xml'/>
<title>
DDFT.wiki
</title>
<link>
https://ddft.wiki/
</link>
<description>
The missing manual for Legacy Doomsday
</description>
<lastBuildDate>
Sat, 20 Jan 2018 23:39:35 +0000
</lastBuildDate>
<generator>
clj-rss
</generator>
<item>
<guid>
https://ddft.wiki/posts-output/DD_2017/
</guid>
<link>
https://ddft.wiki/posts-output/DD_2017/
</link>
<title>
Doomsday in 2017
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;We shall begin with a Pixar-esque bittersweet beginning. The deck is working, people are happy, we can run maindeck Abrupt Decay yet still deploy triple basics to fight the Miracles menace and then bam: Some idiot erects a roadsign and Wizards cripples a lot of creative decks to target a single one, which they fail to kill. Suddenly it's over. So many people, so many of the deck's pilots have had the final straw. They are done, that's it. Game over. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is it the end?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I hope not.....&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;2017 has been a difficult year for Doomsday as an archetype primarily due to the SDT ban. A lot of it was spent trying to work out any and all possible  replacements, both card wise and playstyle wise. A lot of people switched to ANT as in their mind the deck had lost the one benefit over it's bigger sister in terms of card selection, advantage and resilience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I talk with a lot of people about the deck but one of the people I talk most with is Nanda aka Namida. He is a Doomsday veteran who resides in Japan and has always  been a helpful and insightful voice on the Stormboards, TheSource, MtGSalvation forums and on the Doomsday Facebook group. One morning I awoke to find a veritable essay from him and his feelings on where the deck was right now. We had a very big debate over that essay with some strong points and feelings being conveyed from both sides. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will avoid posting the full debate but I do want to use his points to address a lot of the frustrations pilots, both current and old, are having with the deck and hopefully give some comfort to those still playing, maybe even enticing some people back. I am looking to address each point truthfully. Although I have stated my goals I will not sugar coat things and there are some things that cannot be changed about the deck so I am not expecting a mass conversion of people but even if I can persuade one or two, I will be happy!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For many points I will not just be talking shit out of nowhere. Back in November I  started a mini project to begin collecting statistics about the deck and I have put a call out to anyone who can to provide match results for the deck. These results have a number of data points that are needed to be considered &quot;good data&quot;. I also stressed  to all submitting I wanted all reports. All wins, losses, draws. I was not looking to get a rose-tinted view but instead wanted an accurate snapshot of how the deck was performing. This mix of pilots also allowed a mix of experienced and new people to get involved hopefully allowing a wide range of data sources and to minimise pilot variance to allow the deck itself to shine through results wise. The results pool is still small at the time of writing (337 matches recorded) but it still provides a good starting snapshot to get an idea of how the deck is doing. Any results involving the mirror match have been ommitted for any statistics involving game results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although I am presenting these statistics this article is just using them to help answer questions. I am planning to release a full article soon to properly describe and present the data and stats collected from the data so if any explanation is missing regarding the data that is presented here, it should be addressed in this later article.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Withut further ado, and continuing on the Disney theme...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let's get down to business:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are Nanda's opening points:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Building the deck again, I'm still feeling the same issues--basically I'm
frequently getting hands where you have to choose whether or not to stall
out by keeping cantrips as combo pieces or stall out by having no cantrips
when you finally assembled BBB and Doomsday. I'm realizing more how Top set
up a lot of the quick wins by being selection without costing a card to let
you look for Doomsday or Dark Ritual, but also because a lot of my Doomsday
wins were actually off of Burning Wish, Top and LED mana. Getting BBB feels
like a huge choke point for winning quickly. Does that make sense? 
Rituals feel bad, but you need one to actually be fast with Doomsday. 
If I don't open on Ritual and Doomsday in hand I feel stuck between not 
playing cards and hoping to draw into what I need, or playing cards and hoping
that I still have enough resources to win on the same turn by the time I find 
my combo pieces.&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This block actually contains two points in one as I see it. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The deck is inconsistent.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The idea is that you have to choose whether to use cantrips to sculpt or to hold for the combo turn. Doomsday is unique insofar that cantrips double as combo elements to either draw into the stack, exchange between the stack and your hand, draw into a kill elements or draw to win with LM.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will admit that yes, you do have to make these choices however that is unfortunately the core of the deck and the element that makes it unique to both TES and ANT. DDFT probably has the most elements of choice and the most potential decision points per  turn. This is not even taking into account actually resolving the namesake card. Use of cantrips and lands/fetches has always been the hardest element of the deck and the  most crucial. Saying that though, the current iterations of the deck I think play the most number of cantrips of any. Along with the U combo triplet of Brainstorm, Ponder and Gitaxian Probe we also run a number of Preordains and / or Conjurer's Baubles both of which add to the cantrip count. We are, like any deck in a game with some level of variance, at the whimsy of fate however unlike many decks we do have the tools to minimise that variance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To work through this let us start by looking at our levels of variance, specifically, as  Nanda mentioned, our opening hands. Mulligans were tracked across all games of a match and the win percentages calculated from when mulligans occur. Below you can find two graphs: the percentage of games where mulligans occur and the percentage of games won against mulligans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DD2017Graph1.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Mulligan Percentage Across Games&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DD2017Graph2.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Mulligan Win Percentage Across Games&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you can see, despite the concerns, the deck seems to mulligan very well. There could be some variance in that people are keeping dodgy seven card hands for fear of hitting a bad six however with the scry rule in effect, going down to six is certainly not the end of the world. This is also shown to be the case in the second graph. Seven cards have a very good win rate with a heavy reduction as one mulligans to six and to five. One thing to note is how few data points there actually are for mulligans to five or less showing some severe data changes for the win percentage across these points. As a result nothing solid can be inferred from these low points but I I hope the fact that the number of these results being so low is a testament to the general consistency of the deck itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes you will have garbage hands. We run some oddball cards that our often useless outside of an active combo turn and sometimes variance can really kick you in the proverbial nuts but most of the time, at least according to the numbers, we seem to be doing fine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Making BBB for a quick DD without DR is difficult.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the issues with the deck is that the namesake card does require BBB to cast. This is an interesting element with a deck that is primarily U. In terms of options for creating BBB we have Dark Ritual as a four of. Rain of Filth as a potential one of. Lotus Petal as a four of and generally four lands that make B (normally 2 Seas,  1 Badlands and 1 Swamp). Nanda is correct in saying that DR is the best way to make BBB quickly however it is far from the only way. Two lands and a lotus petal is often enough or even one land and two petals can occur often. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;...a lot of my Doomsday wins were actually off of Burning Wish, Top and LED mana.&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also have the option thanks to Conjurer's Bauble to play out Doomsday on turn 2 via Burning Wish and two LEDs thereby replicating the 'saved' draw effect we gained from SDT. One of the more well known recent achievements of the deck, the 5-0 result from an MTGO by g0ld_rook had him run four CB and he noted that he had under appreciated the saved draw effect gained by them during early testing with them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This point feeds into some of Nanda's later comments:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;...&amp;quot;I'm sure the deck is fine if the game is going long, but I feel completely
toothless in the early game. If your hand isn't perfect then you're not 
racing most fast decks, and that means you have to use your cantrips more
aggressively and I don't think that's a winning proposition when every card 
you spend to look is actually costing a full card now.&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which creates a third point:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Doomsday is not a fast enough combo deck.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of the &quot;classic&quot; Legacy storm variants you have three main camps (though some would argue only two). ANT, DDFT and TES. In order of speed it has always been considered to order TES as the fastest, ANT as second and DDFT as the slowest. This has often been true as TES sacrifices deterministic wins for speed and DDFT sacrificed speed for  resiliency and card advantage. Now that SDT is gone where does the deck stand on this scale?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this comparison I will be using data taken from two spreadsheets linked in an article written by Bryant Cook on the TES website. A link will be provided at the end for those  interested in the article. To summarise it; Bryant took game data from a TES pilot and an ANT pilot and compared a number of factors including one listed as &quot;Active Combo turn&quot;. This turn has been tracked on a scale of T1 to T4+ with the theory that beyond T4 there is little difference for a deck concerned about being fast between say T5 and T20. As part of my data gathering I also collected combo turn statistics. This is the turn  the combo occurs so if you are executing a DD Pass-the-turn pile it is the turn you cast Doomsday to make the pile, not the turn you win on. This can create some results skewing but I will address that a bit more in a moment. First let's look at the raw data:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data collated on 03/01/2018:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th align='center'&gt;Deck&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th align='center'&gt;Average Combo Turn&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;ANT&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;3.01&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;DDFT&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;2.95&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;TES&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;2.61&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wait what?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yeah, that's what I said when I first crunched the numbers. How is DDFT, traditionally the slowpoke of the Legacy Storm world being on par if not a tad faster than ANT?! There are a few reasons for this, partially to do with the data skew I mentioned before. This can include turns where we &quot;go off&quot; without winning on that turn. This can mean that the &quot;combo turn&quot; may be the turn before we actually win (potentially as many as  five turns prior to winning) which could skew the data. This also includes us using something in our  arsenal which mimics that which TES has: Burning Wish into Empty the Warrens. This can be an early play which,  even if only making ten or so gobbos can lead to fast wins. This does mean that the data will skew towards earlier turns but also  means the TES data is affected by this bias. In the interest of transparency, it's worth noting that the DDFT data was recorded with a scale of 1-5+ turns, which has been converted to correspond with the TES and ANT range of 1-4+.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When discussing this point regarding speed with Nanda he made the following comments:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Doomsday is being carried on the back of Burning Wish at that point is
how it has been feeling. Not like Doomsday is doing anything powerful, 
but that we're playing a faster Storm deck with pet cards instead of
the cards that make it a consistently fast threat. I've been liking when
I draw Burning Wish in these versions of the deck because we have so much
fast mana. I have felt miserable anytime I had a Doomsday in hand.&amp;quot; ... 
...&amp;quot;I want to be wrong about the deck not winning in a timely manner, but
I can't reconcile the idea that the mana is too awkward for Doomsday
to consistently be a Turn 2/3 threat without having to spend cards you
may not be able to afford spending. That sums up the issue for me, I think.&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This gives us point 4:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Doomsday is now just a worse ANT/TES.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are fair comments. It is true that cards like Past in Flames are incredibly powerful engines that in many situations are less akward and more consistent than Doomsday itself. Our data above including EtW results definately skews it faster so what if we take out those results and consider only the wins that use the deck's namesake card? We'll also have a look at the breakdown in how the deck actually goes about winning to work out how much the statement of...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;...we're playing a faster Storm deck with pet cards instead of the
cards that make it a consistently fast threat...&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;...is true.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th align='center'&gt;Deck&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th align='center'&gt;Average Combo Turn&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;ANT&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;3.01&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;DDFT&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;2.99&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;TES&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;2.61&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Focussing only on the DD winning lines we see the turn average has definately gone up but is still on par with ANT. Following on from this point again Nanda had real concerns that  Doomsday as a deck was not winning using its namesake card. Let's look at the breakdown of  winning game engines:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DD2017Graph3.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Combo Engines Across Games&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I guess that paints a clear picture. The four engines measured are the primary ones of  any line that uses Doomsday itself, BW into EtW, natural ToA kills and then anything else (such as weird SB plans or other alternatives like Telemin Performance). We can see that a vastly overwhelming majority is using the namesake card. Does this make the deck better than the others? No, not inherently. Does it mean that it is unique enough to not be a bad TES/ANT clone? Yes, I think so. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nanda ended his message with the following final point to make:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Sorry for the rant earlier. It's frustrating because it feels like having to learn to
walk after losing a leg. Is no one else feeling this way? I want to stay the course
but I keep getting discouraged by how even just my goldfishing is playing out.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which gives a final point of:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Post SDT ban DDFT is not the same as pre-ban DDFT.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now I have no fancy stats or graphs for this. It's true. DDFT is a different deck now. We have only made a few changes, going from 16 lands to 15, replacing IU with AoI, upping to 4 BW and using Preordain and Conjurer's Baubles but they are noticeable ones and yes, it will take time to re-learn. Cantripping is now even more important, knowing when and how to use each card is key and the sheer number of potential tricks you can do thanks to exiling via AoI is crazy but it does take time. Many, myself included have had to go back to the basics of the deck which can really make you feel down. I don't blame anyone who has put the deck down for good as a result of this frustration. You're not alone. I will however say that DDFT is still alive, it's still relatively competitive (overall match win % at the time of writing is 56.69%) and it is still a lot of fun to play, punishing as all hell when it goes wrong and a highly  rewarding deck when it goes right. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing&amp;#95;thoughts&quot;&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm sorry for this information splurge as it is a lot to take in. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of this article resolving we are left with the following five point stack having been addressed:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;The deck is inconsistent. &lt;strong&gt;No more than any combo deck&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Making BBB for a quick DD without DR is difficult. &lt;strong&gt;Potentially but often not&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Doomsday is not a fast enough deck. &lt;strong&gt;Slower than TES, as fast as ANT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Doomsday is now just a worse ANT/TES. &lt;strong&gt;DDFT is it's own style, not just a clone&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Post SDT ban DDFT is not the same as pre-ban DDFT. &lt;strong&gt;Correct and we as pilots have to work through this&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this has helped you as the reader come to make a decision whether to put the deck down, pick the deck up or just understand what happened to the deck in general. As stated at the start; I have presented a small cross section of statistics to help answer some of these points but these are a small taster of what we have been tracking. In the near future I plan to  write a more detailed article simply going through the stats and giving more information on how they are collected which should help explain any further data bias concerns people might have on what is said here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you wish to contribute to our community data collection for the deck you can find the link to the spreadsheet below.&lt;br /&gt; If you wish to collect the data but not in a public forum then please feel free to take a copy of the spreadsheet and if you could send that link to Doishy via theSource forum or the Stormboards that would be appreciated. A couple of people currently do this for the sake of running their own trending but if we could use the data for overall trending, that would be appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://theepicstorm.com/storm-data-comparison/'&gt;Bryant Cook's Article&lt;/a&gt; spreadsheets visited 03/01/2018&lt;br /&gt; &lt;a href='https://magic.wizards.com/en/articles/archive/mtgo-standings/competitive-legacy-constructed-league-2017-12-10'&gt;g0ld_rook's 5-0 list&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;a href='https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/14hIVFCCxK6v6PHzj_7opfigFWVGV73kv59OdeN-J95I/edit?usp=sharing'&gt;Doomsday Stats Collection Spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<author>
Doishy
</author>
<enclosure>

</enclosure>
<pubDate>
Wed, 10 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
https://ddft.wiki/posts-output/DDBC-001/
</guid>
<link>
https://ddft.wiki/posts-output/DDBC-001/
</link>
<title>
Doomsday by Committee, Setting the Scene
</title>
<description>
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Eye of twilight, give us sight.
Take our offer, give us might.
Make our power tears of night.&amp;quot;
...

&amp;quot;Guys do we intend to try and beckon forth power through the Eye of twilight?&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;Why, what's wrong with the Eye of twilight?&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;I'm sure there are more powerful entities out there.&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;Like whom?&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;Hanarsh the soul taker? We have virgins right here...&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;No! Look, Eye of twilight is the best otherworldly entity that
may be willing to grant unholy power.So he is what we will reach out to. Understand?&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;Fine.&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;Sure.&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;Okay. Where were we....Eye of twilight, give us sight...&amp;quot;
...
&amp;quot;Do we really always have to wear black?&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hello and welcome to the first of what will hopefully be a series of articles whereby some players get together and either observe and discuss live games with DDFT or go over scenarios presented by people. The idea behind this is to try and work through the decision process used by different people, to help highlight how different people think and to hopefully provide meaningful examples that give lessons others can take away and apply to their own play.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this first ritual meeting we have two members of the super-secret-shadowy-Doomsday-cabal (TM)*&lt;br /&gt; d8dk32 and Doishy playing through some games of an MTGO league. Instead of doing a complete breakdown of every game instead we'll just focus on some of the more thought provoking or interesting decision points and provide some insight into our respective discussion of those points and how the decision came about, whether it was correct and whether it worked (because those two can be mutually exclusive!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's d8dk32's list and he is the primary pilot and will be explaining most of the scenarios. Doishy is watching and will add further commentary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The decklist:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/Ritual1_decklist.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;d8dk32's decklist&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;#42;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;em&gt;super-secret-shadowy-Doomsday-cabal (TM) might not exist....&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;scenario&amp;#95;1:&quot;&gt;Scenario 1:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are on the play and started with a Misty Rainforest. Opponent leads Turn one Verdant Catacombs and passes. We play a Badlands, crack the fetch for an Island, and cast Preordain, which brings us to here:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/Ritual1_Scenario1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Scenario 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doishy and I quickly agree that we go for it here. By leaving both cards on top and drawing Doomsday, we can cast Doomsday and win that way if it resolves, and if not we Brainstorm into a Burning Wish for a lethal Tendrils (including the extra storm from the counterspell). In this case, Doomsday resolved and we had to decide how to build our pile. Our storm count was already plenty high so we only needed four cards in the pile to achieve lethal storm. There were two options available to us for what to do with the 5th slot:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A. Hide the Laboratory Maniac at the bottom of the pile.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;B. Use the spare card to Gitaxian Probe to see what they are on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the correct play?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We decided on choice A, to hide the Lab Man, thinking that there was more to be gained from having a trick up our sleeve. We only briefly discussed what the opponent could be on and sort of assumed it was Czech Pile and they got caught with their pants down. For game two we sideboarded conservatively, swapping a Therapy for the sideboard Thoughtseize. Unfortunately, game two was a bit of a blowout that started with a turn one Chalice@1 from the opponent, who of course is playing 4C Loam (Aggro Loam). In hindsight this potentially could have been avoided by choosing choice B.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Knowing how to sideboard properly is important, and losing the suprise factor of the Lab Man plan is insignificant in comparison, especially considering the matchup. Compared to Czech Pile, a deck like 4C Loam requires much more specific sideboarding to fight back in games two and three. Furthermore, this is a good example of how format familiarity goes beyond simply knowing what spells a deck plays. Czech Pile rarely plays more than one or two Verdant Catacombs, if any, whereas it is essentially always a four-of in 4C Loam.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doishy's comments:&lt;br /&gt; *Our discussion was a tad more in depth here. From a previous match we had faced an elves opponent who had started with a dramatically slow opening and so pondered whether this was another elves start. It could also have been Czech Pile who missed the Ponder/Deathrite opening or even some sort of Aggro Loam or Maverick build. Small mention was also put towards Turbo Depths however most of these decks have enough one drops to make it strange to not play something. In hindsight we for sure should have gone for Option B, especially given most relevant boarding from our opponent is based upon the other fifty nine cards they will see over the one they won't. Information is crucial and seeing seven points of information is much better than hiding one.*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;scenario&amp;#95;2:&quot;&gt;Scenario 2:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is our turn three in game two vs Elves. They have Gaea's Cradle, Cavern of Souls, Wirewood Symbiote and Quirion Ranger in play, with Dryad Arbor and Cabal Therapy in hand. Our board consists of tapped Tropical Island, untapped Swamp, and Lotus Petal, and our hand is Brainstorm, Doomsday, and Dark Ritual. Our life total is still relatively high so we have an easy opening for a pass-the-turn pile with Lab Maniac. The important question here is what to put in the pile. To answer this question, we need to consider what disruption they could have and what of that we can even play around.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/Ritual1_Scenario2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Scenario 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pile that quickly jumps to mind is a 'basic' pile like [AoI, LED, LM, GP, GP]. This neatly plays around Therapy, and the 4 life paid is fine in this situation. The problem with this pile is it requires the use of the Petal to cast AoI, meaning they'll have a turn to find something like Reclamation Sage for the blowout.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You could build [LED, AoI, LED, GP, LM] and use the Brainstorm in hand to kick things off next turn. This doesn't require the use of the Petal but could be ruined if they find a black mana source to cast Therapy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They could potentially draw Surgical Extraction as well. Using the Brainstorm in hand to draw into the pile would improve the odds of getting the right cards even if the our pile got shuffled.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We thought for a bit about what pile would beat the most kinds of hate but just went with the 'basic' Maniac pile since Therapy seemed most likely happen and to avoid running down the clock too much. This pile ended up working fine, but no sooner had we committed to it than Doishy came up with a better pile: [Volc, AoI, LM, LED, GP]. With this, we can hold the Brainstorm and if they Therapy or play artifact destruction on their turn simply cast Brainstorm off Petal to draw the Volcanic Island, dodging both kinds of hate. Volc will be the red source for AoI next turn. Otherwise, we'll hang onto the brainstorm until our next turn. Draw the Volc, crack the petal to brainstormn into AoI, play the Volc and win. If at any point they cast Surgical, we Brainstorm after it resolves and hope the pieces we need are in the top three.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doishy's comments:&lt;br /&gt; *We dicussed the different interactions that could be found with Natural Order being the primary one. Natural order finding a Craterhoof would just kill us there and then so that is one thing we basically had to ignore (assuming the opponent had retained the card in their deck post board). Normally Reclamation Sage is a one of in the SB but, alongside Green Sun's Zenith which is normally a three to four of the odds of finding it were higher. This does not even count for them finding something like an Elvish Visionary and starting an &quot;Engine&quot; turn. I think the Volc line was the safest choice given the inherent risk of a pass the turn pile against a deck that can literally explode from nowehere.*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;scenario&amp;#95;3:&quot;&gt;Scenario 3:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We've just lost game one to RUG Delver and are in the process of sideboarding. The question of whether to bring in Xantid Swarm comes up. It is obviously powerful if it sticks around, but dies easily to Bolt. This can be a difficult matchup if the RUG player has a countermagic-loaded hand. After some discussion we decide to bring in Swarm, reasoning that Bolt is only four cards and their only good way to remove it. Our game two mull to six let us cast Swarm on turn one, with Ritual and a Wish already in hand, a good start. However the Swarm immediately dies to Bolt, leaving us way behind on tempo and vulnerable to Wastelands since we had to use Tropical Island. It's possible that playing Swarm right away was incorrect, but since the aim was to go off in the next turn or two it seemed best to run it out immediately.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So back to the question at hand, is Xantid Swarm good against RUG Delver, and Delver decks more broadly? I think the answer is &quot;no&quot;. I used to think of Swarm as an easy solution for all manner of blue decks but this discussion has started to change my opinion. Xantid Swarm is a less popular choice for Storm sideboards lately but Delver will often keep Bolts anyway as a hedge against Xantid Swarm and as reach. Swarm can also be blocked by flipped Delvers, which decreases its usefulness in the pre-combo turns. Finally, against Delver variants in general, countermagic is expected and we can fight through that; it's the additional axis they attack on that causes the problem. In RUG, this is mana denial, and in Grixis, this is discard. Swarm doesn't really help against either of these. I think these sideboard slots could be used in a better way, although I'm not quite sure how yet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doishy's comments:&lt;br /&gt; *I personally was against Swarm coming in. Locally my meta is full of Grixis Delver variants and all run Bolt, even post board as, if nothing else, it forces us to consider whether we can go off and lose half our life in the face of a potential three damage, especially if relying on Probes. As part of our discussion on this we actually went and checked the sideboard of every top placing, large event Storm deck to see what they were running in terms of sideboards and whether Swarm was a heavy feature. Many didn't run any or ran only a Miser's copy. This actually kick started some faulty chicken-and-egg logic. We reasoned that because Storm doesn't play a lot of it now, the opponent would likely not be prepared to face it. What we should have considered was that maybe not many were being played because Bolt was so prevalent.*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;bonus&amp;#95;discussion:&quot;&gt;Bonus Discussion:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the four rounds we played, Doishy noticed that I was bringing in Thoughtseize every round and suggested I play it maindeck. In the past I have been averse to playing Thoughtseize anywhere in the seventy-five because I thought the two life would relevant. It took a lot to convince me to even play it in the sideboard, so the idea of maindecking it never crossed my mind. However, if you're sideboarding something in every single match, you ought to at least consider maindecking it. As such, I am now testing three Duress, three Therapy, one Thoughtseize main, with the fourth Therapy in the board. The two life from Thoughtseize has not been as relevant as I anticipated and the flexibility it provides is useful. Not needing to guess what hatebear an opponent is holding, being able to take a Snapcaster that would flashback a Flusterstorm, being able to see the opponent's hand before deciding whether to take Force of Will or Leovold, all of these are realistic scenarios where Thoughtseize is potentially better than Duress or Therapy. However, the life loss would quickly add up so I don't think I want it in multiples just yet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doishy's comments:&lt;br /&gt; *This observation was in some part due to the fact that d8 would not simply add in an extra discard spell but swap it out for a Therapy. There was also some bias here as for the last year I have been running a Miser's Thoughtseize main and it whas been very strong, especially in the face of Thalias or Eidolons so much so that I have consider switching from three Therapy, two Duress one Thoughtseize main to three Therapy, one Duress and two Thoughtseize main.*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;parting&amp;#95;thoughts:&quot;&gt;Parting Thoughts:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;d8dk32's comments:&lt;br /&gt; I often talk to myself when I play online, but it's much more informative to talk to someone else who also knows your deck. Hopefully reading this and any future articles we publish will help people learning to play this deck, but I think this pair-playing process is a valuable learning tool and if you can find a willing partner would be an excellent way to learn on your own. Just as important as learning to build piles is learning how to make the plays in the early turns to reach the point where you get to build piles. Having someone to watch over your shoulder helps you play better by catching mistakes and providing a sounding board when the best line isn't clear. Doishy and I agreed on most things this time but discussing the reasoning behind our choices is helpful regardless.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doishy's comments:&lt;br /&gt; *I for one really enjoyed watching d8 play whilst we discussed decisions. What made me feel confidant was, barring some of the decision points above, we quite often agreed very quickly on what line to take with most being the correct one. In addition to the above we had a classic turn two &quot;Do we jam?&quot; vs what turned out to be an Esper Stoneblade/Delver variant. We both said yes and it was 100% correct given the circumstances. One thing that it made clear to me is how important it is having these very fluid conversations during gameplay. Although people at my local shops know me and my deck of choice none of them really &quot;know&quot; the deck to the point where I could properly discuss my card choices, play choices and similar.*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hopefully you enjoyed this first installment of Doomsday by Committee. We shall hopefully return with more of the super-secret-shadowy-Doomsday-cabal (TM) that might not exist with further discussion on other play points, opening hands, scenarios and occasional puzzles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<author>
d8dk32, Doishy
</author>
<enclosure>

</enclosure>
<pubDate>
Wed, 03 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
