<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss version='2.0' xmlns:atom='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'>
<channel>
<atom:link href='https://ddft.wiki/' rel='self' type='application/rss+xml'/>
<title>
DDFT.wiki
</title>
<link>
https://ddft.wiki/
</link>
<description>
The missing manual for Legacy Doomsday
</description>
<lastBuildDate>
Sun, 25 Mar 2018 19:58:31 +0000
</lastBuildDate>
<generator>
clj-rss
</generator>
<item>
<guid>
https://ddft.wiki/posts-output/SCG_Worcester_Report/
</guid>
<link>
https://ddft.wiki/posts-output/SCG_Worcester_Report/
</link>
<title>
The End of the World at SCG Worcester: A Tale of Heroic Courage and Crushing Defeat
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;Our hellride begins on March 3rd, 2018, just after 12am. I have to be up in 5 hours to start making my way towards Worcester. I throw my shit in a bag and climb into bed, where I promptly fall asleep but wake up an hour before my alarm. Portents of things to come. At 5am I crawl out of bed, take my dog out, and get in my car.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I drive an hour and a half to a teammate's house where we condense into 2 cars (there's 8 in our group), grab some breakfast, and start driving. I had hoped to use this time to try to sleep a bit more but instead we screech along to Limp Bizkit songs and &quot;What's New, Pussycat&quot; as sung by Tom Jones and Engelbert Humperdinck and arrive at the venue feeling refreshed and ready for 9 grueling rounds of magic. I scribble out this decklist:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;3 Doomsday
4 Burning Wish
1 Act on Impulse
1 Laboratory Maniac
4 Gitaxian Probe
4 Brainstorm
4 Ponder
3 Preordain
2 Conjurer's Bauble
4 Duress
3 Cabal Therapy
4 Dark Ritual
4 Lion's Eye Diamond
4 Lotus Petal
4 Polluted Delta
3 Scalding Tarn
1 Misty Rainforest
2 Underground Sea
1 Badlands
1 Volcanic Island
2 Island
1 Swamp

SIDEBOARD
1 Doomsday
1 Tendrils of Agony
1 Act on Impulse
1 Massacre
1 By Force
1 Thoughtseize
1 Empty the Warrens
2 Hurkyl's Recall
1 Chain of Vapor
1 Echoing Truth
2 Abrupt Decay
1 Tropical Island
1 Sylvan Library
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;And the hellride begins in earnest. This is all from sketchy notes and memory, so bear with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;scg&amp;#95;worcester&amp;#95;legacy&amp;#95;open&quot;&gt;SCG Worcester Legacy Open&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r1&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;aluren&amp;#95;(0-2)&quot;&gt;R1 vs Aluren (0-2)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: I lose the roll and keep a hand with a Doomsday, a Cabal Therapy, and a couple of cantrips. They lead on Tropical Island into DRS. I cantrip and pass. They play a land and maybe a cantrip or something and pass. I Probe them and see Aluren, Harpy, a Brainstorm, and they have a blue source available. I cantrip and set up a kill for next turn, electing not to Therapy because they'll just hide things with Brainstorm and I want to protect my combo next turn. Naturally, I don't get a next turn. They Brainstorm end of turn, untap, and play Aluren and Recruiter and I scoop.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-1 Preordain, -1 Conjurer's Bauble, -1 Island&lt;br /&gt; +1 Thoughtseize, +1 Abrupt Decay, +1 Tropical Island&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: I get stuck on 1 land for approximately a year. In the top 9 cards of my deck I manage to draw both Lab Maniac and Act on Impulse but not another land. I am never really in this game and I get combo'd out around turn 5.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-1. Great Start.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r2&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;uw&amp;#95;stoneblade&amp;#95;(2-0)&quot;&gt;R2 vs UW Stoneblade (2-0)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: I lose the roll again. We both cantrip a bit and around turn 3 I cast a discard spell. They're left without interaction and I Brainstorm into a natural Tendrils kill on turn 4.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-1 Preordain, -2 Lotus Petal, -1 Island&lt;br /&gt; +1 Thoughtseize, +1 Abrupt Decay, +1 Sylvan Library, +1 Tropical Island&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: I mull to 5. My notes are sketchy but it looks like they got out Stoneforge into Batterskull and took me to pound town for a couple turns, but I manage to go off with just 3 life left. They Brainstorm in response to my Doomsday but don't draw countermagic and I get there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-1. Hopefully the start of something truly beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r3&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;miracles&amp;#95;(2-1)&quot;&gt;R3 vs Miracles (2-1)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: I win the roll. They get Search for Azcanta down on turn 2. I feel pressured to make a move or get buried in card advantage once it flips. I make a pass-the-turn pile on t4 that lets me Duress first for some protection. I take a Counterspell but they brainstorm into a Force and shut me down.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-2 Lotus Petal, -2 Preordain, -1 Island&lt;br /&gt; +1 Thoughtseize, +2 Abrupt Decay, +1 Tropical Island, +1 Sylvan Library&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: Early on I Duress a Force and land Library, which their Flusterstorms can't counter. I aggressively draw cards with Library and around turn 5 I Discard one of their Flusters, bait another with Doomsday, and natural Tendrils them out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G3: This game plays out similarly to g2. I get the Library down and see a ton of cards with it. Sometime after turn 5 I have a Bauble on board, and a hand of 2x LED, Ritual, Doomsday, Preordain, Wish, Duress. I take a Fluster, leaving them with another. I Jam the Doomsday into it, and they let it resolve. I build a pile of &lt;code&gt;Duress, AoI, LED, LED, Wish&lt;/code&gt;. Tap Bauble to draw the Duress and take the 2nd Fluster, then play out my LEDs, Preordain into the Act on Impulse, and go off.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-1. Things are looking up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r4&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;death&amp;#95;and&amp;#95;taxes&amp;#95;(1-2)&quot;&gt;R4 vs Death and Taxes (1-2)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: I lose the roll and mull to 6. My hand can make 10 goblins on turn 1 or cantrip and try to set up a deterministic turn 2 kill. They lead on Plains and Mom and I agonize over what to do. If they have Stoneforge, 10 gobs won't win, but if they have Thalia I'll have to spend the Wish in my hand getting Massacre instead of business. I decide not to make goblins and cantrip instead, and they drop Thalia. I wish for Massacre and they drop Recruiter and get Prelate. I Massacre, they Prelate on 4 which I can mostly ignore. I have a turn or 2 where if I find a Doomsday I probably win, but my cantrips come up blank and they get Spirit of the Labyrinth and Revoker on LED and we go to game 2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-1 Island, -4 Duress, -1 Preordain&lt;br /&gt; +1 Thoughtseize, +1 Tropical Island, +2 Abrupt Decay, +1 Chain of Vapor, +1 Echoing Truth&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: I make 12 Goblins turn 2 on the play and Flashback a Therapy. It gets there a couple turns later.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G3: My hand make 12 Goblins t1 on the draw. Again, this is not enough if they have turn 2 Stoneforge into Skull, but I got punished for not jamming in G1 and it seems more likely to me that they would prioritize keeping hate over keeping Stoneforge. I make my gobs, and they drop Stoneforge and stabilize.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-2. It's crazy how much worse 2-2 feels compared to 2-1. I now have to win 5 in a row to make Day 2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r5&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;ur&amp;#95;delver&amp;#95;(2-1)&quot;&gt;R5 vs UR Delver (2-1)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: I win the roll but can't find discard to get through their Force of Will and they Delver me out of the game.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-1 Preordain&lt;br /&gt; +1 Thoughtseize&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: They have no threats but a stacked hand of Fluster, 3x Daze, 2x Force. However, without a clock I have plenty of time and am able to make my land drops, find some discard, and eventually can go off through the last Daze or 2 left. My opponent seems upset and has me walk through the combo twice just to make sure they're really dead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G3: I present my deck and my opponent picks it up and starts counting the cards. They seem pretty salty and people who fish for shitty wins like this bother me so I ask to see their Delvers to go with the checkbox cards. Neither of us turn up anything illegal. They get a threat down turn 1 and start clocking me. I Duress on turn 2 and see their hand is Fluster, 2x Surgical, 2x Bolt. I get the Fluster, then the next turn they tap out for a Stormchaser Mage. I Therapy on turn 3 and they fire off both Surgicals, taking irrelevant cantrips in my grave. This lets me hit both Bolts, so they can't kill me when I Doomsday. They attack me down low, I untap, and start going off. I wish for Tendrils, and say &quot;Tendrils you for 20?&quot; They count up all the spells I cast and gleefully inform me that I am short on storm and only got 18. I remind them that their life total is like 12 after those Surgicals and it doesn't fucking matter because they're still dead. After they sign the slip and flee, I count up my storm and it was in fact the full ten drills.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-2. Time to ride the lightning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r6&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;bomberman&amp;#95;(2-1)&quot;&gt;R6 vs Bomberman (2-1)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: I lose the roll and am looking at a Mentor and 3 monk tokens by the time it's my turn. I play Island and Ponder. On their turn they drop some 0-cost artifact and hit me for 9. I untap, cantrip, don't find anything, and we go to game 2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-3 Cabal Therapy, -1 Preordain&lt;br /&gt; +1 Thoughtseize, +2 Hurkyl's Recall, +1 Echoing Truth&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: I Duress a LED from their hand and they play Salvagers without any payoff. We draw go for a while and I get beat with Salvagers. I have the most of the combo in hand but am tight on mana and need a Ritual. They find another LED and go infinite with a Mishra's Bauble to draw most of their deck in my upkeep. Fortunately, I draw an extremely timely Ritual and blow them away with a simple storm kill.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G3: They lead on Mentor again make a couple tokens. I have discard and a cantrip. I'm a bit worried about Chalice or Canonist but I figure if they had it, they wouldn't have led on Mentor, so I skip the discard and cantrip, setting up a turn 2 kill. On their turn they drop Tormod's Crypt and Engineered Explosives, which both do very little besides jack up their Monks. I take a big hit but still have enough life to kill with Doomsday, Ritual, and 2 Probes in hand.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;4-2. The Dream lives on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r7&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;miracles&amp;#95;feat.&amp;#95;back&amp;#95;to&amp;#95;basics&amp;#95;and&amp;#95;nahiri&amp;#95;(2-0)&quot;&gt;R7 vs Miracles feat. Back to Basics and Nahiri (2-0)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: I win the roll and start with a cantrip. They play Strand and pass, so I put them on Miracles, which is correct. I Duress them and see they have maindeck B2B, which is annoying because I like to be able to fetch nonbasics vs Miracles. They don't have any countermagic however, and on turn 4 I have a 2nd discard spell to make sure the coast is still clear, and then win with a very basic storm kill.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-2 Lotus Petal, -2 Preordain, -1 Island&lt;br /&gt; +1 Thoughtseize, +2 Abrupt Decay, +1 Tropical Island, +1 Sylvan Library&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: Sideboarding doesn't change despite the B2Bs, it just means you need to be more careful with how you fetch, and you may need to take B2B over countermagic with your discard. This time they have countermagic but I get it with the discard. The rest of their hand is a bit clunky, with B2B, Nahiri, Entreat, and Jace. They draw and tap out for B2B, which catches one of my Seas tapped. I have another land to play though, and I decide it's now or never and jam the combo. I have Ritual, Doomsday, Brainstorm, and Burning Wish in hand with an Island and a Sea untapped. This is a standard Brainstorm Pile so I'll let the reader figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;5-2. Two more and I get to keep playing tomorrow. Just need to keep hitting good matchups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r8&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;eldrazi&amp;#95;aggro&amp;#95;(2-1)&quot;&gt;R8 vs Eldrazi Aggro (2-1)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: I lose the roll vs a bad matchup. My hand is decent, probably a turn 3 sort of hand. They lead on Tomb into Mimic. I have a Therapy, which I cast naming TKS, thinking if they had Chalice they would have played it. I hit one, but they peel another on their turn and take my Burning Wish. They have a Smasher to follow it up and I die before I can get anything together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-3 Cabal Therapy, -2 Preordain, -1 Bauble, -1 Island&lt;br /&gt; +1 Tropical Island, +2 Abrupt Decay, +2 Hurkyl's Recall, +1 Echoing Truth, +1 Thoughtseize&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: I cantrip on my turn and set up for t2 Empty the Warrens. They start with a land that only makes one mana, and pass. I probe them in the process of making 16 goblins and see some fat Eldrazi, a Warping Wail, a Thorn, and some more lands that only make 1 mana. Looks like they were hoping to have a 2nd turn. The goblins get there without incident.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G3: My 7 is 3 lands, Hurkyl's Recall, Ritual, LED, Doomsday. SNAP KEEP. They lead on Chalice@0 and a Cavern. I play land and pass. They play a Factory and pass, presumably leaving up Warping Wail. I play another land and pass. I need to draw a cantrip to complete my combo. They don't have a 3rd land and keep holding up 2 mana. I draw a Probe and drop my 3rd land, ready to cast Recall. On their turn, they still don't find another land but they do tap out for Thorn of Amethyst. In their end step, I crack a fetch, Recall their board away, untap and win. I Probe them to draw into my pile and see they did indeed have the Warping Wail, and tapping out for the Thorn let me catch them with their pants on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;6-2. I have reached the win-and-in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r9&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;jim&amp;#95;davis&amp;#95;on&amp;#95;miracles&amp;#95;feat.&amp;#95;b2b&amp;#95;(1-2)&quot;&gt;R9 vs Jim Davis on Miracles feat. B2B (1-2)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I look at my pairings for the final round and see I am against Jim Davis, which is a name I recognize. Looks like I'm not going to get to play some chump. As I'm making my way to my table, I hear my name and table number called to the feature match area. Unfortunately it's like the backup to the backup feature match, so there is no footage of me playing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: I lose the roll and Jim leads on Strand, fetch Island, cast Portent. This at least screams that he's on miracles. We play draw-go for a bit. I resolve a Bauble. Several turns into the game, he does something funky, Brainstorming with an Azcanta trigger on the stack. On my next turn, I get a look at his hand and see he has just one Force of Will. My hand is LED, LED, Wish, Ritual, Doomsday and I have UBR available. I Ritual out the Doomsday, and he sits and thinks long enough that the judge prompts him to make a play. He decides to Force the Doomsday, and I play out my LEDs, Wish for another Doomsday, and go off. He mentions that he made a mistake and got too cute with the Brainstorm/Azcanta thing and would have had another counterspell if he hadn't. I didn't really follow what he was saying because I was more focused on my sideboarding, but I believe him. That's how Storm works though; make a little slip-up and an experienced Storm player will punish you for it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-2 Lotus Petal, -2 Preordain, -1 Island&lt;br /&gt; +1 Thoughtseize, +2 Abrupt Decay, +1 Tropical Island, +1 Sylvan Library&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: My opening 7 is Probe, Probe, Ritual, Doomsday, Brainstorm, Underground Sea, Fetch. He starts with land and a cantrip. I listen to the voices of the cosmos telling me, &quot;Jam the fucking turn 1 kill, no guts no glory, you brought Doomsday and you are 6-2, don't start acting like a sane person now.&quot; The voices make a compelling argument, and even if my Doomsday gets countered I still have a Brainstorm and Probes. I run out the Doomsday and it gets Forced. The game goes on for quite a bit longer. I eventually draw Sylvan Library, but it gets countered. Then an Azcanta comes down, flips quickly, and I get slowly buried under card advantage. It's possible jamming the turn 1 here was wrong, but I'm not the kind of guy to turn down a turn one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G3: He has a turn 2 Search for Azcanta but is filling the grave relatively slowly. I take some countermagic out of his hand, and around turn 4 or 5 there is a window of a turn or 2 where if I draw a cantrip I can get a clean win. Unfortunately I don't draw the cantrip, Azcanta flips, and I start getting buried. Most of his Azcanta activations find him cantrips, but those cantrips turn into mystery cards. I draw a lot of mana, no discard, and 2 Baubles. He gets a Clique out and leaves my Doomsday and ritual in hand, which is a real bad sign, but at this point he'd been Azcanta-ing for 6+ turns and I'm sure his hand was well stocked. We go to time and on turn 0 of turns, I'm dead on board to Clique, so I make move. With 2 Bauble on board, if the top 2 cards of my deck are Burning Wishes, I have an ouside shot at winning if he somehow only has a couple counterspells. I play out a couple LEDs I'd picked up, then ritual into Doomsday. It gets countered. I crack my LEDs and then draw with a Bauble. I peel a Wish, but it gets countered. I crack the other Bauble but it just draws me a Cabal Therapy. I drop it on the table and he shows me his hand that still has a ton of counterspells. GG Jim Davis, the Dreamkilller.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final Day 1 Record:&lt;/strong&gt; 6-3/14-10.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thus ends my run in the Open, but there is still more Magic to be played tomorrow. I meet up with my teammates and we head off to dinner. I've been saying all day that I'm going to get hammered whether I Day 2 or not, but I end up drinking responsibly and eating this insane burger with tuna and pork belly and a fried egg, plus blackberry champagne barbecue sauce, whiskey cheddar, red onions, sauteed mushrooms, and tomato. If you're ever in Worcester, Massachusetts, go to The Fix. It's good, but a little pricey.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We head back to our hotel and crash for the night. I wake up around 4 am and feel like I need to cast Obliterate on the toilet. After about 10 minutes of only being able to cast Death Cloud (which apparently woke up one of my teammates) I crawl back into bed, and toss and turn until about 6:30am when I get up to shower.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We grab breakfast and walk over to the venue. I sell a few EDH staples I'll never use and get a foil Lab Maniac and a foil Empty the Warrens. Then I scribble out my decklist for the legacy Classic. I decided to drop the green splash this time, to compare the two versions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;3 Doomsday
4 Burning Wish
1 Act on Impulse
1 Laboratory Maniac
4 Gitaxian Probe
4 Brainstorm
4 Ponder
3 Preordain
2 Conjurer's Bauble
3 Duress
4 Cabal Therapy
4 Dark Ritual
4 Lion's Eye Diamond
4 Lotus Petal
4 Polluted Delta
3 Scalding Tarn
1 Bloodstained Mire
2 Underground Sea
1 Badlands
1 Volcanic Island
2 Island
1 Swamp

SIDEBOARD
1 Doomsday
1 Tendrils of Agony
1 Act on Impulse
1 Massacre
1 By Force
1 Thoughtseize
3 Empty the Warrens
2 Hurkyl's Recall
1 Chain of Vapor
1 Echoing Truth
1 Rending Volley
1 Telemin Performance
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;I almost fall asleep at my table for the players meeting. I drink half an energy drink, and sit down for the first round of the Classic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;scg&amp;#95;worcester&amp;#95;legacy&amp;#95;classic&quot;&gt;SCG Worcester Legacy Classic&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r1&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;grixis&amp;#95;dreadstill&amp;#95;(0-2)&quot;&gt;R1 vs Grixis Dreadstill (0-2)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: I win the roll, keep 6, and then look at it a little closer and realize it has no lands. Oops. It does have a petal and a Ponder, so I Ponder and miss a land. Draw another Petal on my next turn, use it to Preordain, and find an Underground Sea. I Probe them and see Standstill, Force and Stifle. I blew so many resources trying to fix my stupid hand that I am way behind. They drop Standstill, effectively ending the game. I finally find a second land but it's a fetch and will just eat a Stifle. I scoop before I give away that I'm not just on ANT.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-2 Preordain -1 Burning Wish&lt;br /&gt; +1 Thoughtseize, +2 Empty the Warrens&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: My hand is much better this time. I Duress and take some countermagic. On their second turn, they tap out to cast a Phyrexian Dreadnought and stifle it's sacrifice trigger. On my third turn I make 12 goblins, thinking I can just chump the Dreadnought and win with gobs. I then learn Dreadnought has trample. I consider throwing all my goblins in front of it when it attacks, but I'm empty handed and I know they have a Standstill in hand so I just scoop since I played like a donkey.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-1. gReAt StArT.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r2&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;punishing&amp;#95;dack&amp;#95;(2-1)&quot;&gt;R2 vs Punishing Dack (2-1)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I go to my seat for the match and find 2 people already shuffling up in it. I ask them what the deal is, and it turns out one is my opponent and the other is supposed to be sitting a seat over. Except there is no seat over. The signs for the table numbers are all fucked up and there isn't room for everyone at the table. We grab a judge, get it sorted out, and end up at a random open table with a 5 minute time extension.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: My opener has 3 discard spells, 3 lands, and a Doomsday. I Just make land drops, point a discard spell at my opponent every so often, and eventually draw into what I need for a clean storm kill and finish them off around turn 6 or 7.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-2 Preordain, -1 Burning Wish&lt;br /&gt; +1 Thoughtseize, +2 Empty the Warrens&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: It takes me a while to work through their countermagic. At one point I try to bait a Force with an extra LED, but it resolves and gets stolen by Dack. I didn't expect this to matter. It's late in the game but I make 12 goblins since they only have a Dack and a Strix on board and 1 card in hand. However, that one card is Snapcaster Mage. With 3 lands untapped, on my end step they Snap targeting Kolaghan's Command, use the stolen LED mana to cast it, shocking me and regrowing an Izzet Staticaster they had looted away earlier. A pretty sweet line which I totally missed and walked right into. My goblins die and we move to the third game.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G3: They are beating me down with a strix and a DRS but are a little constrained on mana. I get the interaction out of their hand, they Surgical my Duresses, and I go for a pass-the-turn pile of &lt;code&gt;Therapy, AoI, LM, LED, GP&lt;/code&gt; with 4 lands and a Bauble on board, and another Doomsday in hand. This gives me a discard spell to try to hit a counterspell if they draw one. However, they draw and play Dack, and Dack me. I draw Therapy and AoI, and discard Therapy and the extra Doomsday. I untap, draw Lab Man, play AoI exiling LED and Probe, and crack LED for UUU discarding Lab Man. Bauble puts Lab Man on the bottom of my emty library so I draw it, cast it, and use Probe from exile to draw for the win. Miss me with that Dack shit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-1. Maybe I can get my head back in the game.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r3&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;mono&amp;#95;red&amp;#95;stompy&amp;#95;(0-2)&quot;&gt;R3 vs Mono Red Stompy (0-2)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: I lose the roll, they lead on Chalice@1, and I can't cast any of my spell in hand. Turn 2 Rabblemaster into turn 3 Chandra ends the game in short order. I only play lands, and only a Volc and some Grixis fetches, so my identity remains a mystery.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-4 Cabal Therapy, -1 Conjurer's Bauble&lt;br /&gt; +2 Hurkyl's Recall, +1 Echoing Truth, +1 Chain of Vapor, +1 Thoughtseize&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: I fetch and Thouhgtseize away a chalice, leaving them with a Sudden Shock, a Chandra, and a Fiery Confluence. They just play lands and I cantrip. On turn 3 I make a pass the turn pile, except I'm at 17 life so I drop to 8. End of turn they Sudden Shock me, untap, and cast Fiery Confluence to burn me for the last 6. So I played like an ass and got punished for it again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-2. I'm a Saltfield Recluse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here I do quick maths and it looks like even if I win out, X-2 may not even make top 16, and I can't stop fucking up so there's no way I'll win out. I decide to drop, eat a real lunch instead of a bag of beef jerky like the day before, cruise the vendor tables for an hour or so and join a 4-round Legacy Challenge to try to dump on my fellow scrubs who scrubbed out of the Open and the Classic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I changed my decklist one more time, leaving the maindeck untouched from last time but swapping the 2 extra ETW in the board for 2 Defense Grids.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;SIDEBOARD
1 Doomsday
1 Tendrils of Agony
1 Act on Impulse
1 Massacre
1 By Force
1 Thoughtseize
1 Empty the Warrens
2 Defense Grid
2 Hurkyl's Recall
1 Chain of Vapor
1 Echoing Truth
1 Rending Volley
1 Telemin Performance
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;side&amp;#95;event:&amp;#95;4-round&amp;#95;challenge&quot;&gt;Side Event: 4-Round Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r1&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;spanish&amp;#95;inquisition&amp;#95;(2-0)&quot;&gt;R1 vs Spanish Inquisition (2-0)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: I'm playing against one of my teammates who also is a scrub and I know he's on SI. I win the roll and blind-Therapy Dark Ritual. I miss, he shoots off a draw 4 but draws trash and I untap and get to hit with my next Therapy. This buys me another turn and I win by Wishing up a Doomsday and storming out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-1 Conjurer's Bauble&lt;br /&gt; +1 Thoughtseize&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: He has a Draw4 on turn 1 but draws garbage again. We rip eachother's hands apart with discard and start a topdeck war. I eventually find a Wish, go to grab a Doomdsay and... shit it's not there. I forgot to put it back in my board after last game. I just have to pass, but my opponent can't draw a business spell to save his life and I topdeck one of my four (lol) Doomsdays to win two turns later.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-0. Easy to beat a bad storm deck when you're playing a slightly less bad storm deck.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r2&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;manaless&amp;#95;dredge&amp;#95;(2-1)&quot;&gt;R2 vs Manaless Dredge (2-1)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: I lose the roll but my opponent puts me on the play so I know what to look for in my opener. My 7 is strong, with a few cantrips, a ritual, and an LED so I just need a business spell. Unfortunately I cantrip and cantrip and never find business, and they do their dredge thing and shred my hand and I lose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-1 Preordain&lt;br /&gt; +1 Thoughtseize&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: I remember to put myself on the draw and Duress on my first turn. Their hand is all creatures, so I don't get to timewalk them. On my 2nd turn I make a pass-the-turn Maniac pile, which is safe from everything but the nuttiest of dredges. The dredging was far from nutty, and my Lab Man won me the game on my turn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G3: I'm on the play and my hand has a Doomsday, a Brainstorm, some lands, and 3 discard spells. All my discard spells function as timewalks, and I naturally draw into what I need to storm out on turn 4.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0. Glad I dropped from that stupid Classic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r3&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;burn&amp;#95;(2-0)&quot;&gt;R3 vs Burn (2-0)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: I win the Roll and I cantrip. They start off with a suspended Rift Bolt. I cantrip again. They don't have turn2 Eidolon and just hold up 2 mana. On my turn 3 I go off with a double cantrip pile. I probe and see 3 Price of Progress and a Fireblast but it isn't enough to kill me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-1 Lab Maniac, - 2 Duress&lt;br /&gt; +1 Thoughtseize, +1 Chain of Vapor, +1 Echoing Truth&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: They lead on fetch, pass. I blind-Therapy Eidolon and miss. They don't have a second land. I Ponder and they hit it with a Pyroblast, but still don't draw a 2nd land for their turn. On my turn 3 I make 16 Goblins and flashback 2 Therapy to shred their hand. The second land comes way too late to matter against 14 goblin tokens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-0. Still not regretting dropping from the Classic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;r4&amp;#95;vs&amp;#95;bug&amp;#95;control&amp;#95;(0-2)&quot;&gt;R4 vs BUG Control (0-2)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;My opponent declines to draw and would rather play for glory. Fine by me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G1: My opponent plays a Delta and passes. My hand is something like Sea, Island, Ritual, Therapy, Petal, LED, Wish. This makes 12 goblins turn 1 with the Therapy for protection if they let Ritual resolve. I ritual, it resolves. I therapy and name force. Their hand is Brainstorm, 2x JTMS, strix, and some lands. I keep going, and in response to Wish my opponent Brainstorms and hits Force of Will. Oh well. I play it out for a bit but once Jace comes down I just scoop because my hand wasn't going anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-3 Preordain&lt;br /&gt; +1 Thoughtseize, +2 Defense Grid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;G2: I resolve a defense grid but my hand is not coming together the way I wanted. They have a deathrite shaman and a strix pressuring my life a bit. I make a pass-the-turn pile, but fail to account for the possibility of Jace. Of course, Jace is cast and I get fatesealed and I scoop. My pile was `AoI, LED, LM, GP, GP`. If I had simply put one of those Probes on the top, I would have likely won this game. Oh well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So a 3-1 record in the challenge is good enough for some prize wall tickets, which i use to get 12 Ixalan boosters. While I'm cracking them, the Open Top 8 is being announced: &quot;And in 7th seed, JIM DAVIS!&quot; I respond by yelling &quot;FUCK JIM DAVIS!&quot; and get lots of dirty looks. Jim Davis, if you read this for some reason, you were a pleasant opponent and I'm glad you did well on day 2. I don't hate you, I just hate that you took my day 2 from me. Asshole.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Match Record:&lt;/strong&gt; 10-6 (62.5% winrate)&lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Total Game Record:&lt;/strong&gt; 22-18 (55% winrate)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;thoughts&amp;#95;on&amp;#95;the&amp;#95;deck&amp;#95;going&amp;#95;forward&quot;&gt;Thoughts on the Deck Going Forward&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;62.5% winrate is respectable, and the fact that I had a win-and-in is encouraging in terms of the deck's viability. With the exception of my R1 match against Aluren, my 2 other losses on day 1 felt winnable, with a bit better luck. Luck and tight play are both needed to succeed in large tournaments, and I feel like I played tight, at least on day 1. The deck can be quite fatiguing to play even for an experienced pilot, so proper sleep and nutrition is important.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the decklist itself, I was pleased with my list for the main event. I wish the green splash wasn't needed because I hate having a land in my sideboard, but Miracles is growing in popularity and I am loath to be cold to counterbalance. Sylvan Library is an excellent card, and if you expect lots of slow blue control decks, and are already splashing green, it's probably worth the slot. The only change I would consider making to the sideboard is moving the Tropical Island to the main to free up a slot for something to help against Delver, but I'm not sure what and I really like 3 basics in the main. I'm pretty sure the maindeck is exactly what I want, except the 8th fetchland should probably be a Tarn instead of a Misty or a Mire. But I only own 3 Tarns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lists, particularly the sideboards, I played in the Classic and the Challenge I didn't like quite as much. Multiple ETW is an OK plan vs Delver-type decks, but it can make some clunky draws and Doomsday doesn't utilize them as well as TES does. I don't think I like it enough anymore. Similarly, Defense Grid and Xantid Swarm look pretty good on paper but they have their own issues. Grid comes down too late, especially if you need to play it through Daze, and then opponents start being able to pay for it. Swarm dies to bolt which Delver should be keeping in against us, and requires the green land vs a Wasteland deck. I think what I really need is more practice against Delver decks so I can just tighten up play and gain a few percentage points rather than some magical sideboard card. My matchup against UR and RUG Delver feel fine, it's really just Grixis Delver with the discard where I feel unfavored.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this gives anyone on the fence about sleeving the deck up a reason to take it for a spin. Practice and experience can help you go a long way, and if nothing else the deck is a blast, and peoples' reactions when you cast Doomsday are fun. I recall both my round 7 and 8 opponents expressing that they'd rather be knocked out by Doomsday than some boring mainstream strategy, and god knows I'd rather eat shit playing Doomsday than cruise to victory in a Honda Civic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<author>
d8dk32
</author>
<enclosure>

</enclosure>
<pubDate>
Tue, 06 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
https://ddft.wiki/posts-output/DDStatistics-001/
</guid>
<link>
https://ddft.wiki/posts-output/DDStatistics-001/
</link>
<title>
Doomsday by Numbers
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;All data compiled 3rd February 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Decks not hot.
DDFT is international now fam.
Check the statistekks. &amp;#40;?&amp;#41;&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;the&amp;#95;data&amp;#95;collection&quot;&gt;The Data Collection&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back in January I posted an &lt;a href='https://ddft.wiki/posts-output/DD_2017/'&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; detailing a bit about DDFT as a deck across the course of 2017 and how it is fairing now. I presented some statistics that had been gathered and gave a hint that another article was coming where I present them properly and in greater detail.&lt;br /&gt; This is that article.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back in November some of us started trying to actually work out how well the deck was performing. We had gone through a tricky year with the Sensei's Diving Top ban and as a result many people were changing many things in their lists with no real idea of how performance was going. To help work this out we started a public data collection sheet to facilitate working out a variety of stats. A lot of influence for what data was to be gathered stemmed from the equivalent data sheets and statistical work by Bryant Cook of TES fame.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are some key differences in how we have collected certain things. It was assumed that DDFT of the three storm decks (ANT, DDFT, TES) was the slowest and therefore unlike ANT/TES, we wanted to record combo turns up to T5+ as opposed to T4+. The reasoning behind this is that T4 can often represent a combo turn on T3 where the pilot has identified a piece of permission they must play around or similar. Despite this difference in raw data for any direct comparisons to the ANT/TES data we have converted the results so that it's all incorporated into the T1-T4+ format.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Quick glossary:
ANT - Ad-Nauseum Tendrils, a Legacy Storm deck based around Past in Flames engine
DDFT - Doomsday Fetchland Tendrils, a Legacy Storm deck based around the card Doomsday
TES - The Epic Storm, a Legacy Storm deck based around Ad Nauseum and Burning Wish
Tendrils/ToA - Shorthands for Tendrils of Agony
Empty/EtW - Shorthands for Empty the Warrens
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Winning game engines was another difference. We could have just tracked Doomsday vs Empty the Warrens vs Natural Tendrils kills however this wouldn't have been enough detail. Doomsday itself is a weird deck, once you cast the card there are so many different ways to draw into it, time it, win with it that you have a lot of different options. In total we have 35 different generic winning engines used spread across the use of Doomsday, Burning Wish and the various win conditions that can be utilised. We also tracked whether a combo turn involved a &lt;a href='http://ddft.wiki/pages-output/ch1/pass-the-turn/'&gt;pass-the-turn pile&lt;/a&gt;,  a &lt;a href='http://ddft.wiki/pages-output/ch1/basics/'&gt;double cantrip pile&lt;/a&gt;, and various other techniques with cards like &lt;a href='http://ddft.wiki/pages-output/ch1/laboratory-maniac/'&gt;Laboratory Maniac&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href='http://ddft.wiki/pages-output/ch2/cb-piles/'&gt;Conjurer's Bauble&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Going into this level of detail allowed us to identify trends in how often the deck uses what to win and how useful certain niche cards are to the deck.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The full public data spreadsheet may be found &lt;a href='https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/14hIVFCCxK6v6PHzj_7opfigFWVGV73kv59OdeN-J95I/edit?usp=sharing'&gt;HERE&lt;/a&gt;. Please feel free to contribute any and all matches played, just make sure to include all information requested in the sheet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;bias&amp;#95;within&amp;#95;the&amp;#95;data&quot;&gt;Bias Within the Data&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are some limitations with how our data is compiled and assessed. One major one is in regards to combo turn. Combo turn refers to the turn we &quot;go off&quot; but this may not be the same turn we win. Casting Doomsday on T1 to build a &lt;a href='http://ddft.wiki/pages-output/ch2/shelldock-emrakul/'&gt;Shelldock Isle/Emrakul Pile&lt;/a&gt; would still be recorded as a T1 combo turn despite not winning until T3/4.  The same with early EtW plays. Making 14 Goblins on T2 might not win you the  game until T4 or even later but it would still be recorded as T2. The TES data has this same issue in regards to EtW lines but with Doomsday and pass-the-turn piles it's possibly a bit more prevalent here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another major difference in the data collection compared to Cook's TES data is that the TES data only draws from a single individual and only records MTGO Leagues or Comp REL paper events. We decided to be a bit more open with our data collection compiling it from a large number of individuals at various experience levels with the deck, and from various types of events. This also includes practice games, testing, local Paper events, Xmage and Cockatrice games. Despite some of the stigma associated with some of these mediums they are all valid matches played in a competitive fashion so should be counted. It also allows us to generate the most amount of data points to try and avoid individual or medium biases so that the deck's performance is the focus irrespective of skill level or experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final main limitation is what decklists people are running. DDFT has a core series of pieces however unlike a lot of decks, there are a lot of 'flexible slots' available in terms of numbers of Burning Wishes, Lotus Petals, Lands, having BR duals vs all UR duals, whether you run Rain of Filth, Conjurer's Bauble, Preordain, how many discard spells you run and at what ratios of each and splash colours. Because of this variance it's hard to determine what list is performing best. We could try at give each ratio of things a unique code slot and string them together just as we could try and get people to list all cards in their piles however people don't want to have to keep that level of detail in their notes so in the interests of pragmatism this level of data is ommitted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;business&amp;#95;business&amp;#95;business.&amp;#95;numbers,&amp;#95;numbers,&amp;#95;numbers&quot;&gt;Business Business Business. Numbers, Numbers, Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Right then, let's start looking at some data shall we?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First of all the number of total 'good' match data points is 565. A 'good' match is defined as one where we have all the pertinent information recorded. For any data crunching involving sucess or win% we shall also define a 'good' match as &quot;not the mirror&quot;. The reason being here is that we might only have data from one side of the match therefore only recording the result from one side and not the other. As a result it's easier to just omit them than allow the minor skew from it to be used. So for any results based statistics we had 560 data points instead (Yes, that means 5 mirror matches played, funtimes!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;winning&quot;&gt;Winning&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;First of all the ones that everyone wants to know: The Match and Game win rates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Match Win rate (%): 56.25%&lt;br /&gt; Game Win rate (%): 54.71%&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well it's positive(&gt;50%)! That's always a good start.&lt;br /&gt; What does this actually mean though?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well it means that we have a better than half chance of winning any given match against a 'normal' metagame at least at face value. As you can see we have some interesting points in regards to the fact our game win % is lower than our match win % and this will become more apparent as we go on. Long story short is that we are favoured to win the less games we play. Most of our wins are 2-0's and most of our losses are 1-2's.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DDStatsTable1.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Ratio of wins table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is further justified when we look at our Match win % when we go to a game 3 compared to when we do not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Match Win rate win in two games (%): 61.62%&lt;br /&gt; Match Win rate win in three games (%): 50.54%&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking further in again to a win % breakdown by game, we can see the trend even clearer:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Game 1 wins (%): 61.15%&lt;br /&gt; Game 2 wins (%): 51.64%&lt;br /&gt; Game 3 wins (%): 50.74%&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So why is this?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It might be that many of our opponents have relevant sideboard choices against us. It could also represent them incorrectly sideboarding and realising their choice was wrong for game 3. A great example of this would be bringing in Grafdigger's Cages or similar, then realizing that grave hate is generally ineffective. It could also be related to the fact that the archetype has quite a few unknown cards which our opponent's might not know how to interact with but, as the match goes on, will get used to. It might also be our own constraints in sideboard options. Being a combo deck, and a combo deck that uses a wishboard at that, we do have limited slots and options for trying to face a large variety of hate in different forms and it may be often we just have the wrong answers at the wrong times. It could also be the fact that our main win condition allows our opponent to see the entierity of our deck that is not included in the Doomsday pile and thus know exactly what to play around.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;*Pre-release edit:&lt;br /&gt; I had in fact pre-written a lot of this article before copying in the numbers as the trends were already seemingly well developed however something was interesting to note here. When I first started writing this up G3 was at a negative win% (around 45%) however when coming to review the article we realised that it was now at 50%. This is really interesting as it implies that, over the course of the past month or so, we as an archetype and as pilots have obviously started figuring things out. My personal hypothesis is that we, having finally worked out where the deck is going have now been able to focus outwards at the person across the table and not just inwards in trying to get the deck to work. This change over time is about to be discussed next anyways but I thought it was an interesting enough point to mention.*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;about&amp;#95;time&quot;&gt;About Time&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Backtracking a tad, the overall Match Win % is not static however. We have been trending it over time and, although we have only recently started gathering data, we can already see some trends for the better. Below shows the Match Win % over time; I have also presented the number of matches played over time to allow you to get a feel for how significant each month's result is in terms of consistency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DDStatsGraph1.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Match win % over time&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DDStatsGraph2.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Number of matches over time&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you can see with have limited early data but a lot more recent data. We can also see an upward trend in terms of Match Win %. If we look at Match Win % but only taken from the past two months we get:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Match Win rate win past two months (%): 58.67%&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Definitely looking better.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So why is this improving? I personally thing it's to do with consistency. Previously between April (Top ban) and around late October there was little agreement between pilots who talked things through about what to run. Many lists were tried in order to work out where the deck was going and whether it was still viable, and though there was some early success, those lists tended to vary wildly. As touched on in my last article a lot of experienced people also put down the deck and though it still attracted newer pilots, a lot of the experience was lost and those who remained had to re-learn a lot of things and get used to playing the deck without Sensei's Top.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Part of this also might be the widespread accepted use of Conjurer's Bauble as a card. The innocuous little artifact has a lot of potential and some key niche uses for the deck. Some people had started to use it but it wasn't until g0ld_rook's 5-0 league online being reported that people started to adopt it a lot more. It might be unrelated to this addition but that is one of the few decklist additions we can track with relative certainty mainly through discussions between pilots.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;the&amp;#95;other&amp;#95;side&amp;#95;of&amp;#95;things&quot;&gt;The Other Side of Things&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Obviously one thing we can consider in how a deck is performing and it performs over a given period of time is the opposition that the deck will face. Despite what some people might say, there is no deck that has good matchups against every other deck. That is the beauty of the game and of the format, there is something to prey on and be hunted by. If I were to go into a room and be told I was playing against Elves and Lands I would be very happy. If I was told it was Eldrazi and Force of Will/Hymn to Tourach/Ethersworn Canonist.dec then I would be less so.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First of all let's take a moment to appreciate the variety of the format. Across the results we have a total of 97 different decks which is great. We did go through the results and tidy up certain decks where minor naming coventions might give the illusion of difference but they are the same for all intents and purposes (Dragon Stompy and Goblin Stompy). I'm sorry if by doing this I offend any archetypes however sometimes key subtle differences are just too subtle. The highest represented deck across all our results only had a net share of 9.04% of the meta we have faced so far which is nice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now if we were to split our dicussion for each deck we would have a hard time and this would be a much longer article (though it is pretty long anyways so thank you if you have made it this far). Often when talking about archetypes people will split them into 'Blue' and 'Not Blue'. Sometimes this binary system gets broadened by the addition of 'Chalice' however this then asks the question of where does Popeye stompy circa 2017 fit in being both 'Blue' and a 'Chalice' deck?&lt;br /&gt; Poor taste jokes aside we decided we wanted to try and define what we were facing by more than just whether they had a colour associated with them but less than listing each and every archetype.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We decided upon a system of defining archetypes by what elements we as a deck actually cared about in terms of interaction. We decided to use the following catergories to list archetypes by:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Chalice - Decks that utitlise permanent, usually artifact based hate such as  Chalice of the Void or Thorn of Amethyst&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Counterspells - Decks that utilise reactive countermagic such as Force of Will  or Daze&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Discard - Decks that utilise proactive hand disruption such as Thoughtseize or  Hymn to Tourach&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Hatebears - Decks that usitilise creature based disruption such as Thalia,  Guardian of Thraben or Eidolon of the Great Revel&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Speed - Decks that just try and kill you quickly&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course we then also added sub categories of the combinations of the two so Doomsday as a deck would come under the heading of 'DiscardSpeed'. We did not go for combinations of three because it did not seem pertinent. Only a few decks run a mixture of three of these items (Esper Stoneblade/Deathblade) and of those two are normally more prevalent than the last. Assigning these labels this way grouped interesting things together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite one being a great matchup and the other being unfavorable, both Eldrazi and Lands come under the heading 'Chalice'. Eldrazi because they run Chalice of the Void in the maindeck and Lands because their main method of hate is bringing in Sphere effects from the sideboard. Pretty much all storm variants come under 'DiscardSpeed' but so does BR Reanimator. There are definately limitations to this assigning method and I would be very open to a different way of doing it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking at the performance breakdown against our categories we get this results display:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DDStatsGraph3.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Win % against hate types&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We seem to have a pretty good set of matchups despite the differing hate types however one result is really key in showing how the deck's performance is in this current meta. 'CounterspellsDiscard' is representative of two of the biggest decks in the format right now. Grixis Delver and Czech Pile. We obviously need to try and up our game against these decks however facing a mix of proactive disruption to your hand and reactive countermagic for the combo whilst under pressure is tricky. These are also the category the two highest opposing decks fall into accounting for 16.82% of the meta between them. The 'ChaliceCounterspells' result can be largely discounted due to small sample size, since few decks (mainly Tezzeret lists) run this combination of interaction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just going by the numbers it looks like if we can improve these two matchups specifically then our overall performance rating should increase. The trick is figuring out how to achieve that improvement...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;mulling&amp;#95;over&amp;#95;things&quot;&gt;Mulling Over Things&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my previous article I already showed how the deck mulligans well but let's look into it a bit closer. Again I will present below the graph of percentage of times we keep starting hands and how often we win with said starting hand numbers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DDStatsGraph4.gif&quot; alt=&quot;% Mulligans across games&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DDStatsGraph5.gif&quot; alt=&quot;% Wins based on mulliganes across games&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you can see we keep seven card hands pretty consistently. Interestingly enough, the rate at which we mulligan seems to definitely follow a trend as games go on through a match. This could be because of awareness of opposing deck and what constitutes a &quot;good&quot; hand against a given opponent or it could be more aggressive mulliganing to try and find key sideboard elements. Looking at the win % based on starting hand we continue to see a drop in win percentage across all starting hand sizes. Given the higher penchant for needing to mulligan this might help explain the lower game 3 win % or it might be a result of it rather than a contributing factor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Either way it looks like the deck mulligans pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;gotta&amp;#95;go&amp;#95;fast&quot;&gt;Gotta Go Fast&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next thing to look at that I touched upon previously is the speed that we go off. This is an interesting one as discussed because it's hard to get an accurate representation of speed without fudging numbers or recording exactly what turn you combo off in. For reasons already mentioned the speed of the deck was tracked as the turn that the deck &quot;went off&quot; that is to say completed their combo (whatever combo that was). This includes casting Doomsday to win that turn, casting it to initiate a pass-the-turn pile, delivering a lethal natural Tendrils kill or creating a number of goblins via EtW.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scale was tracked from turn 1 (T1) to turn 5+ (T5+) and is recorded as a percentage of across all games.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DDStatsGraph6.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Combo turn across games&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those are some nice curves no?&lt;br /&gt; Already we can see some interesting observations. Game 1 seems to have the most consistent setup with high percentages of T2 and T3 combo turns. Game 2 seems to show the highest variance with the highest percentage of T1 combos but also a high number of T5+ combos. Let's look more closely at the averages of this graph.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Totalling all combo turns across all games together and applying the TES T1-T4+ scale we can work out our overall Average Combo Turn (ACT).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ACT: 2.94&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comparing this to the other data from the last article we can see we are slower than TES on average but marginally faster than ANT. One thing to note however is that we do record combo turns for games even when we do not win them. This represents us 'going off' and maybe being blown out by an unknown piece of hate or miscounting storm or messing up the pile. To fix this we can generate the ACT filtered only by when we win the game we go off.&lt;br /&gt; Averaging that gives us the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ACT (Wins): 2.92&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you can see it is in fact slightly faster. I think this can be easily explained by the fact that as any game drags on, the non 'fast' combo player is more likely to draw into resistance or answers and apply more pressure at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally we shall check what happens for only winning lines that use Doomsday as the engine card. This is to help get an idea of how many results are being skewed by fast EtW engines being used. Again this is only for games that we win and only where Doomsday is part of the engine used:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ACT (wins, Doomsday): 2.96&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly it is slower than the overall wins ACT however it is still faster than the total ACT compiling all combo turns that include losses. I think all this shows that overall we are a fast enough deck to be considered 'fast combo' (relative to the other storm variants and not including things like Belcher or BR Reanimator).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One thing to consider about the Doomsday only wins number and the others before it is that pass-the-turn Doomsday lines can also skew the data to seem faster than it is. Let's take this as an oppotunity to look at roughly what amount of our total Doomsday lines are pass-the-turn ones.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DDStatsGraph7.gif&quot; alt=&quot;% of PTT piles vs same turn piles&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Game 1 only 20% of play lines are pass-the-turn. Games 2 and 3 this increases to 30% which is interesting. This could be an increase of usage of Shelldock Isle or of Jamming T1 Dark Ritual into a T2 Laboratory Maniac kill against decks that can't effectively interact with that plan early on. It could also represent the need to go off in the face of more constrained resources preventing a same-turn win.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;how&amp;#95;we&amp;#95;do&amp;#95;things&quot;&gt;How We Do Things&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following on from our glance at how often we pass-the-turn we can also see what methods we use to win. We asked people to fill in their winning line from a pretty comprehensive list of different methods but for easy viewing we have broken it down into a set of four.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;DD: Any line that wins via the casting of Doomsday&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;EtW: Any line that wins via the casting of Empty the Warrens (without casting  Doomsday)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;N-Storm: Any line that wins via just naturally storming our with Tendrils of  Agony (without casting Doomsday)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Other: Any other win method such as sideboarded &quot;Man Plans&quot; or Burning Wish  for Telemin Performance&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DDStatsGraph8.gif&quot; alt=&quot;% of win types across games&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doomsday lines are a clear majority in terms of winning engine accounting for three quarters on average of our total lines. Next is Empty the Warrens lines resulting in roughly eighteen percent of lines. Natural Tendrils comes in at a strong five percent or so and 'Other' a neat two percent. If nothing else, it's nice to see how significant the namesake card is as a win condition in a deck that has a lot of potential options for play.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Delving into the Doomsday lines themselves we have another split between the main three win conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;ToA: Doomsday stacks resulting in a lethal Tendrils of Agony&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;LM: Doomsday stacks resulting in winning from a Laboratory Maniac&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;SI: Doomsday stacks winning by casting Emrakul, the Aeons Torn off of  Shelldock Isle&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DDStatsGraph9.gif&quot; alt=&quot;% of doomsday pilea across games&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lethal storm is again a clear majority, especially in Game 1. Laboratory maniac is steady across all games accounting for around thirty percent. I know some people debate on whether the inclusion of maniac is worth it but from this data it seems to show that he represents almost a third of wins therefore should probably be included. What is interesting is that the reduction in storm wins from Games 2 and 3 seems to go directly to the added presence of Shelldock Isle wins.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing&amp;#95;thoughts&quot;&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I didn't think I would get so into this whole stats thing but I did. I'm normally a Han Solo, &quot;don't tell me the odds&quot; kind of guy so following numbers was a refreshing change. I'm hopeful that the above helps solidify our position as an &quot;established deck&quot; despite a lack of metagame penetration and / or number of top 8 performances (give us time!). It seems we are doing pretty well and now just need to start polishing up our gameplay and bringing out our anti-'CounterspellsDiscard' tech (IMO it's two Empty the Warrens in our board).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Massive shout outs to all those who have contributed results to this project especialy d8dk32 and Hulahula who are MTGO League Machines! All I ask is that everyone keeps up with the data recording. The more we keep up with this, the more results, the more accurate a snapshot we can keep on how the deck is performing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<author>
Doishy
</author>
<enclosure>

</enclosure>
<pubDate>
Sat, 03 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
https://ddft.wiki/posts-output/DD_2017/
</guid>
<link>
https://ddft.wiki/posts-output/DD_2017/
</link>
<title>
Doomsday in 2017
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;We shall begin with a Pixar-esque bittersweet beginning. The deck is working, people are happy, we can run maindeck Abrupt Decay yet still deploy triple basics to fight the Miracles menace and then bam: Some idiot erects a roadsign and Wizards cripples a lot of creative decks to target a single one, which they fail to kill. Suddenly it's over. So many people, so many of the deck's pilots have had the final straw. They are done, that's it. Game over. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is it the end?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I hope not.....&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;2017 has been a difficult year for Doomsday as an archetype primarily due to the SDT ban. A lot of it was spent trying to work out any and all possible  replacements, both card wise and playstyle wise. A lot of people switched to ANT as in their mind the deck had lost the one benefit over it's bigger sister in terms of card selection, advantage and resilience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I talk with a lot of people about the deck but one of the people I talk most with is Nanda aka Namida. He is a Doomsday veteran who resides in Japan and has always  been a helpful and insightful voice on the Stormboards, TheSource, MtGSalvation forums and on the Doomsday Facebook group. One morning I awoke to find a veritable essay from him and his feelings on where the deck was right now. We had a very big debate over that essay with some strong points and feelings being conveyed from both sides. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will avoid posting the full debate but I do want to use his points to address a lot of the frustrations pilots, both current and old, are having with the deck and hopefully give some comfort to those still playing, maybe even enticing some people back. I am looking to address each point truthfully. Although I have stated my goals I will not sugar coat things and there are some things that cannot be changed about the deck so I am not expecting a mass conversion of people but even if I can persuade one or two, I will be happy!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For many points I will not just be talking shit out of nowhere. Back in November I  started a mini project to begin collecting statistics about the deck and I have put a call out to anyone who can to provide match results for the deck. These results have a number of data points that are needed to be considered &quot;good data&quot;. I also stressed  to all submitting I wanted all reports. All wins, losses, draws. I was not looking to get a rose-tinted view but instead wanted an accurate snapshot of how the deck was performing. This mix of pilots also allowed a mix of experienced and new people to get involved hopefully allowing a wide range of data sources and to minimise pilot variance to allow the deck itself to shine through results wise. The results pool is still small at the time of writing (337 matches recorded) but it still provides a good starting snapshot to get an idea of how the deck is doing. Any results involving the mirror match have been ommitted for any statistics involving game results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although I am presenting these statistics this article is just using them to help answer questions. I am planning to release a full article soon to properly describe and present the data and stats collected from the data so if any explanation is missing regarding the data that is presented here, it should be addressed in this later article.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Withut further ado, and continuing on the Disney theme...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let's get down to business:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are Nanda's opening points:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Building the deck again, I'm still feeling the same issues--basically I'm
frequently getting hands where you have to choose whether or not to stall
out by keeping cantrips as combo pieces or stall out by having no cantrips
when you finally assembled BBB and Doomsday. I'm realizing more how Top set
up a lot of the quick wins by being selection without costing a card to let
you look for Doomsday or Dark Ritual, but also because a lot of my Doomsday
wins were actually off of Burning Wish, Top and LED mana. Getting BBB feels
like a huge choke point for winning quickly. Does that make sense? 
Rituals feel bad, but you need one to actually be fast with Doomsday. 
If I don't open on Ritual and Doomsday in hand I feel stuck between not 
playing cards and hoping to draw into what I need, or playing cards and hoping
that I still have enough resources to win on the same turn by the time I find 
my combo pieces.&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This block actually contains two points in one as I see it. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The deck is inconsistent.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The idea is that you have to choose whether to use cantrips to sculpt or to hold for the combo turn. Doomsday is unique insofar that cantrips double as combo elements to either draw into the stack, exchange between the stack and your hand, draw into a kill elements or draw to win with LM.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will admit that yes, you do have to make these choices however that is unfortunately the core of the deck and the element that makes it unique to both TES and ANT. DDFT probably has the most elements of choice and the most potential decision points per  turn. This is not even taking into account actually resolving the namesake card. Use of cantrips and lands/fetches has always been the hardest element of the deck and the  most crucial. Saying that though, the current iterations of the deck I think play the most number of cantrips of any. Along with the U combo triplet of Brainstorm, Ponder and Gitaxian Probe we also run a number of Preordains and / or Conjurer's Baubles both of which add to the cantrip count. We are, like any deck in a game with some level of variance, at the whimsy of fate however unlike many decks we do have the tools to minimise that variance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To work through this let us start by looking at our levels of variance, specifically, as  Nanda mentioned, our opening hands. Mulligans were tracked across all games of a match and the win percentages calculated from when mulligans occur. Below you can find two graphs: the percentage of games where mulligans occur and the percentage of games won against mulligans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DD2017Graph1.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Mulligan Percentage Across Games&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DD2017Graph2.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Mulligan Win Percentage Across Games&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you can see, despite the concerns, the deck seems to mulligan very well. There could be some variance in that people are keeping dodgy seven card hands for fear of hitting a bad six however with the scry rule in effect, going down to six is certainly not the end of the world. This is also shown to be the case in the second graph. Seven cards have a very good win rate with a heavy reduction as one mulligans to six and to five. One thing to note is how few data points there actually are for mulligans to five or less showing some severe data changes for the win percentage across these points. As a result nothing solid can be inferred from these low points but I I hope the fact that the number of these results being so low is a testament to the general consistency of the deck itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes you will have garbage hands. We run some oddball cards that our often useless outside of an active combo turn and sometimes variance can really kick you in the proverbial nuts but most of the time, at least according to the numbers, we seem to be doing fine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Making BBB for a quick DD without DR is difficult.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the issues with the deck is that the namesake card does require BBB to cast. This is an interesting element with a deck that is primarily U. In terms of options for creating BBB we have Dark Ritual as a four of. Rain of Filth as a potential one of. Lotus Petal as a four of and generally four lands that make B (normally 2 Seas,  1 Badlands and 1 Swamp). Nanda is correct in saying that DR is the best way to make BBB quickly however it is far from the only way. Two lands and a lotus petal is often enough or even one land and two petals can occur often. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;...a lot of my Doomsday wins were actually off of Burning Wish, Top and LED mana.&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also have the option thanks to Conjurer's Bauble to play out Doomsday on turn 2 via Burning Wish and two LEDs thereby replicating the 'saved' draw effect we gained from SDT. One of the more well known recent achievements of the deck, the 5-0 result from an MTGO by g0ld_rook had him run four CB and he noted that he had under appreciated the saved draw effect gained by them during early testing with them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This point feeds into some of Nanda's later comments:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;...&amp;quot;I'm sure the deck is fine if the game is going long, but I feel completely
toothless in the early game. If your hand isn't perfect then you're not 
racing most fast decks, and that means you have to use your cantrips more
aggressively and I don't think that's a winning proposition when every card 
you spend to look is actually costing a full card now.&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which creates a third point:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Doomsday is not a fast enough combo deck.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of the &quot;classic&quot; Legacy storm variants you have three main camps (though some would argue only two). ANT, DDFT and TES. In order of speed it has always been considered to order TES as the fastest, ANT as second and DDFT as the slowest. This has often been true as TES sacrifices deterministic wins for speed and DDFT sacrificed speed for  resiliency and card advantage. Now that SDT is gone where does the deck stand on this scale?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this comparison I will be using data taken from two spreadsheets linked in an article written by Bryant Cook on the TES website. A link will be provided at the end for those  interested in the article. To summarise it; Bryant took game data from a TES pilot and an ANT pilot and compared a number of factors including one listed as &quot;Active Combo turn&quot;. This turn has been tracked on a scale of T1 to T4+ with the theory that beyond T4 there is little difference for a deck concerned about being fast between say T5 and T20. As part of my data gathering I also collected combo turn statistics. This is the turn  the combo occurs so if you are executing a DD Pass-the-turn pile it is the turn you cast Doomsday to make the pile, not the turn you win on. This can create some results skewing but I will address that a bit more in a moment. First let's look at the raw data:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data collated on 03/01/2018:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th align='center'&gt;Deck&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th align='center'&gt;Average Combo Turn&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;ANT&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;3.01&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;DDFT&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;2.95&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;TES&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;2.61&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wait what?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yeah, that's what I said when I first crunched the numbers. How is DDFT, traditionally the slowpoke of the Legacy Storm world being on par if not a tad faster than ANT?! There are a few reasons for this, partially to do with the data skew I mentioned before. This can include turns where we &quot;go off&quot; without winning on that turn. This can mean that the &quot;combo turn&quot; may be the turn before we actually win (potentially as many as  five turns prior to winning) which could skew the data. This also includes us using something in our  arsenal which mimics that which TES has: Burning Wish into Empty the Warrens. This can be an early play which,  even if only making ten or so gobbos can lead to fast wins. This does mean that the data will skew towards earlier turns but also  means the TES data is affected by this bias. In the interest of transparency, it's worth noting that the DDFT data was recorded with a scale of 1-5+ turns, which has been converted to correspond with the TES and ANT range of 1-4+.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When discussing this point regarding speed with Nanda he made the following comments:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Doomsday is being carried on the back of Burning Wish at that point is
how it has been feeling. Not like Doomsday is doing anything powerful, 
but that we're playing a faster Storm deck with pet cards instead of
the cards that make it a consistently fast threat. I've been liking when
I draw Burning Wish in these versions of the deck because we have so much
fast mana. I have felt miserable anytime I had a Doomsday in hand.&amp;quot; ... 
...&amp;quot;I want to be wrong about the deck not winning in a timely manner, but
I can't reconcile the idea that the mana is too awkward for Doomsday
to consistently be a Turn 2/3 threat without having to spend cards you
may not be able to afford spending. That sums up the issue for me, I think.&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This gives us point 4:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Doomsday is now just a worse ANT/TES.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are fair comments. It is true that cards like Past in Flames are incredibly powerful engines that in many situations are less akward and more consistent than Doomsday itself. Our data above including EtW results definately skews it faster so what if we take out those results and consider only the wins that use the deck's namesake card? We'll also have a look at the breakdown in how the deck actually goes about winning to work out how much the statement of...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;...we're playing a faster Storm deck with pet cards instead of the
cards that make it a consistently fast threat...&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;...is true.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th align='center'&gt;Deck&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th align='center'&gt;Average Combo Turn&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;ANT&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;3.01&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;DDFT&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;2.99&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;TES&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td align='center'&gt;2.61&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Focussing only on the DD winning lines we see the turn average has definately gone up but is still on par with ANT. Following on from this point again Nanda had real concerns that  Doomsday as a deck was not winning using its namesake card. Let's look at the breakdown of  winning game engines:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/DD2017Graph3.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Combo Engines Across Games&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I guess that paints a clear picture. The four engines measured are the primary ones of  any line that uses Doomsday itself, BW into EtW, natural ToA kills and then anything else (such as weird SB plans or other alternatives like Telemin Performance). We can see that a vastly overwhelming majority is using the namesake card. Does this make the deck better than the others? No, not inherently. Does it mean that it is unique enough to not be a bad TES/ANT clone? Yes, I think so. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nanda ended his message with the following final point to make:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Sorry for the rant earlier. It's frustrating because it feels like having to learn to
walk after losing a leg. Is no one else feeling this way? I want to stay the course
but I keep getting discouraged by how even just my goldfishing is playing out.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which gives a final point of:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Post SDT ban DDFT is not the same as pre-ban DDFT.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now I have no fancy stats or graphs for this. It's true. DDFT is a different deck now. We have only made a few changes, going from 16 lands to 15, replacing IU with AoI, upping to 4 BW and using Preordain and Conjurer's Baubles but they are noticeable ones and yes, it will take time to re-learn. Cantripping is now even more important, knowing when and how to use each card is key and the sheer number of potential tricks you can do thanks to exiling via AoI is crazy but it does take time. Many, myself included have had to go back to the basics of the deck which can really make you feel down. I don't blame anyone who has put the deck down for good as a result of this frustration. You're not alone. I will however say that DDFT is still alive, it's still relatively competitive (overall match win % at the time of writing is 56.69%) and it is still a lot of fun to play, punishing as all hell when it goes wrong and a highly  rewarding deck when it goes right. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing&amp;#95;thoughts&quot;&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm sorry for this information splurge as it is a lot to take in. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of this article resolving we are left with the following five point stack having been addressed:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;The deck is inconsistent. &lt;strong&gt;No more than any combo deck&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Making BBB for a quick DD without DR is difficult. &lt;strong&gt;Potentially but often not&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Doomsday is not a fast enough deck. &lt;strong&gt;Slower than TES, as fast as ANT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Doomsday is now just a worse ANT/TES. &lt;strong&gt;DDFT is it's own style, not just a clone&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Post SDT ban DDFT is not the same as pre-ban DDFT. &lt;strong&gt;Correct and we as pilots have to work through this&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this has helped you as the reader come to make a decision whether to put the deck down, pick the deck up or just understand what happened to the deck in general. As stated at the start; I have presented a small cross section of statistics to help answer some of these points but these are a small taster of what we have been tracking. In the near future I plan to  write a more detailed article simply going through the stats and giving more information on how they are collected which should help explain any further data bias concerns people might have on what is said here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you wish to contribute to our community data collection for the deck you can find the link to the spreadsheet below.&lt;br /&gt; If you wish to collect the data but not in a public forum then please feel free to take a copy of the spreadsheet and if you could send that link to Doishy via theSource forum or the Stormboards that would be appreciated. A couple of people currently do this for the sake of running their own trending but if we could use the data for overall trending, that would be appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://theepicstorm.com/storm-data-comparison/'&gt;Bryant Cook's Article&lt;/a&gt; spreadsheets visited 03/01/2018&lt;br /&gt; &lt;a href='https://magic.wizards.com/en/articles/archive/mtgo-standings/competitive-legacy-constructed-league-2017-12-10'&gt;g0ld_rook's 5-0 list&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;a href='https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/14hIVFCCxK6v6PHzj_7opfigFWVGV73kv59OdeN-J95I/edit?usp=sharing'&gt;Doomsday Stats Collection Spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<author>
Doishy
</author>
<enclosure>

</enclosure>
<pubDate>
Wed, 10 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
https://ddft.wiki/posts-output/DDBC-001/
</guid>
<link>
https://ddft.wiki/posts-output/DDBC-001/
</link>
<title>
Doomsday by Committee, Setting the Scene
</title>
<description>
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Eye of twilight, give us sight.
Take our offer, give us might.
Make our power tears of night.&amp;quot;
...

&amp;quot;Guys do we intend to try and beckon forth power through the Eye of twilight?&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;Why, what's wrong with the Eye of twilight?&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;I'm sure there are more powerful entities out there.&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;Like whom?&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;Hanarsh the soul taker? We have virgins right here...&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;No! Look, Eye of twilight is the best otherworldly entity that
may be willing to grant unholy power.So he is what we will reach out to. Understand?&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;Fine.&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;Sure.&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;Okay. Where were we....Eye of twilight, give us sight...&amp;quot;
...
&amp;quot;Do we really always have to wear black?&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hello and welcome to the first of what will hopefully be a series of articles whereby some players get together and either observe and discuss live games with DDFT or go over scenarios presented by people. The idea behind this is to try and work through the decision process used by different people, to help highlight how different people think and to hopefully provide meaningful examples that give lessons others can take away and apply to their own play.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this first ritual meeting we have two members of the super-secret-shadowy-Doomsday-cabal (TM)*&lt;br /&gt; d8dk32 and Doishy playing through some games of an MTGO league. Instead of doing a complete breakdown of every game instead we'll just focus on some of the more thought provoking or interesting decision points and provide some insight into our respective discussion of those points and how the decision came about, whether it was correct and whether it worked (because those two can be mutually exclusive!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's d8dk32's list and he is the primary pilot and will be explaining most of the scenarios. Doishy is watching and will add further commentary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The decklist:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/Ritual1_decklist.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;d8dk32's decklist&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;#42;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;em&gt;super-secret-shadowy-Doomsday-cabal (TM) might not exist....&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;scenario&amp;#95;1:&quot;&gt;Scenario 1:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are on the play and started with a Misty Rainforest. Opponent leads Turn one Verdant Catacombs and passes. We play a Badlands, crack the fetch for an Island, and cast Preordain, which brings us to here:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/Ritual1_Scenario1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Scenario 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doishy and I quickly agree that we go for it here. By leaving both cards on top and drawing Doomsday, we can cast Doomsday and win that way if it resolves, and if not we Brainstorm into a Burning Wish for a lethal Tendrils (including the extra storm from the counterspell). In this case, Doomsday resolved and we had to decide how to build our pile. Our storm count was already plenty high so we only needed four cards in the pile to achieve lethal storm. There were two options available to us for what to do with the 5th slot:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A. Hide the Laboratory Maniac at the bottom of the pile.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;B. Use the spare card to Gitaxian Probe to see what they are on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the correct play?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We decided on choice A, to hide the Lab Man, thinking that there was more to be gained from having a trick up our sleeve. We only briefly discussed what the opponent could be on and sort of assumed it was Czech Pile and they got caught with their pants down. For game two we sideboarded conservatively, swapping a Therapy for the sideboard Thoughtseize. Unfortunately, game two was a bit of a blowout that started with a turn one Chalice@1 from the opponent, who of course is playing 4C Loam (Aggro Loam). In hindsight this potentially could have been avoided by choosing choice B.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Knowing how to sideboard properly is important, and losing the suprise factor of the Lab Man plan is insignificant in comparison, especially considering the matchup. Compared to Czech Pile, a deck like 4C Loam requires much more specific sideboarding to fight back in games two and three. Furthermore, this is a good example of how format familiarity goes beyond simply knowing what spells a deck plays. Czech Pile rarely plays more than one or two Verdant Catacombs, if any, whereas it is essentially always a four-of in 4C Loam.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doishy's comments:&lt;br /&gt; *Our discussion was a tad more in depth here. From a previous match we had faced an elves opponent who had started with a dramatically slow opening and so pondered whether this was another elves start. It could also have been Czech Pile who missed the Ponder/Deathrite opening or even some sort of Aggro Loam or Maverick build. Small mention was also put towards Turbo Depths however most of these decks have enough one drops to make it strange to not play something. In hindsight we for sure should have gone for Option B, especially given most relevant boarding from our opponent is based upon the other fifty nine cards they will see over the one they won't. Information is crucial and seeing seven points of information is much better than hiding one.*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;scenario&amp;#95;2:&quot;&gt;Scenario 2:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is our turn three in game two vs Elves. They have Gaea's Cradle, Cavern of Souls, Wirewood Symbiote and Quirion Ranger in play, with Dryad Arbor and Cabal Therapy in hand. Our board consists of tapped Tropical Island, untapped Swamp, and Lotus Petal, and our hand is Brainstorm, Doomsday, and Dark Ritual. Our life total is still relatively high so we have an easy opening for a pass-the-turn pile with Lab Maniac. The important question here is what to put in the pile. To answer this question, we need to consider what disruption they could have and what of that we can even play around.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/Ritual1_Scenario2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Scenario 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pile that quickly jumps to mind is a 'basic' pile like [AoI, LED, LM, GP, GP]. This neatly plays around Therapy, and the 4 life paid is fine in this situation. The problem with this pile is it requires the use of the Petal to cast AoI, meaning they'll have a turn to find something like Reclamation Sage for the blowout.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You could build [LED, AoI, LED, GP, LM] and use the Brainstorm in hand to kick things off next turn. This doesn't require the use of the Petal but could be ruined if they find a black mana source to cast Therapy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They could potentially draw Surgical Extraction as well. Using the Brainstorm in hand to draw into the pile would improve the odds of getting the right cards even if the our pile got shuffled.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We thought for a bit about what pile would beat the most kinds of hate but just went with the 'basic' Maniac pile since Therapy seemed most likely happen and to avoid running down the clock too much. This pile ended up working fine, but no sooner had we committed to it than Doishy came up with a better pile: [Volc, AoI, LM, LED, GP]. With this, we can hold the Brainstorm and if they Therapy or play artifact destruction on their turn simply cast Brainstorm off Petal to draw the Volcanic Island, dodging both kinds of hate. Volc will be the red source for AoI next turn. Otherwise, we'll hang onto the brainstorm until our next turn. Draw the Volc, crack the petal to brainstormn into AoI, play the Volc and win. If at any point they cast Surgical, we Brainstorm after it resolves and hope the pieces we need are in the top three.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doishy's comments:&lt;br /&gt; *We dicussed the different interactions that could be found with Natural Order being the primary one. Natural order finding a Craterhoof would just kill us there and then so that is one thing we basically had to ignore (assuming the opponent had retained the card in their deck post board). Normally Reclamation Sage is a one of in the SB but, alongside Green Sun's Zenith which is normally a three to four of the odds of finding it were higher. This does not even count for them finding something like an Elvish Visionary and starting an &quot;Engine&quot; turn. I think the Volc line was the safest choice given the inherent risk of a pass the turn pile against a deck that can literally explode from nowehere.*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;scenario&amp;#95;3:&quot;&gt;Scenario 3:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We've just lost game one to RUG Delver and are in the process of sideboarding. The question of whether to bring in Xantid Swarm comes up. It is obviously powerful if it sticks around, but dies easily to Bolt. This can be a difficult matchup if the RUG player has a countermagic-loaded hand. After some discussion we decide to bring in Swarm, reasoning that Bolt is only four cards and their only good way to remove it. Our game two mull to six let us cast Swarm on turn one, with Ritual and a Wish already in hand, a good start. However the Swarm immediately dies to Bolt, leaving us way behind on tempo and vulnerable to Wastelands since we had to use Tropical Island. It's possible that playing Swarm right away was incorrect, but since the aim was to go off in the next turn or two it seemed best to run it out immediately.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So back to the question at hand, is Xantid Swarm good against RUG Delver, and Delver decks more broadly? I think the answer is &quot;no&quot;. I used to think of Swarm as an easy solution for all manner of blue decks but this discussion has started to change my opinion. Xantid Swarm is a less popular choice for Storm sideboards lately but Delver will often keep Bolts anyway as a hedge against Xantid Swarm and as reach. Swarm can also be blocked by flipped Delvers, which decreases its usefulness in the pre-combo turns. Finally, against Delver variants in general, countermagic is expected and we can fight through that; it's the additional axis they attack on that causes the problem. In RUG, this is mana denial, and in Grixis, this is discard. Swarm doesn't really help against either of these. I think these sideboard slots could be used in a better way, although I'm not quite sure how yet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doishy's comments:&lt;br /&gt; *I personally was against Swarm coming in. Locally my meta is full of Grixis Delver variants and all run Bolt, even post board as, if nothing else, it forces us to consider whether we can go off and lose half our life in the face of a potential three damage, especially if relying on Probes. As part of our discussion on this we actually went and checked the sideboard of every top placing, large event Storm deck to see what they were running in terms of sideboards and whether Swarm was a heavy feature. Many didn't run any or ran only a Miser's copy. This actually kick started some faulty chicken-and-egg logic. We reasoned that because Storm doesn't play a lot of it now, the opponent would likely not be prepared to face it. What we should have considered was that maybe not many were being played because Bolt was so prevalent.*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;bonus&amp;#95;discussion:&quot;&gt;Bonus Discussion:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the four rounds we played, Doishy noticed that I was bringing in Thoughtseize every round and suggested I play it maindeck. In the past I have been averse to playing Thoughtseize anywhere in the seventy-five because I thought the two life would relevant. It took a lot to convince me to even play it in the sideboard, so the idea of maindecking it never crossed my mind. However, if you're sideboarding something in every single match, you ought to at least consider maindecking it. As such, I am now testing three Duress, three Therapy, one Thoughtseize main, with the fourth Therapy in the board. The two life from Thoughtseize has not been as relevant as I anticipated and the flexibility it provides is useful. Not needing to guess what hatebear an opponent is holding, being able to take a Snapcaster that would flashback a Flusterstorm, being able to see the opponent's hand before deciding whether to take Force of Will or Leovold, all of these are realistic scenarios where Thoughtseize is potentially better than Duress or Therapy. However, the life loss would quickly add up so I don't think I want it in multiples just yet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doishy's comments:&lt;br /&gt; *This observation was in some part due to the fact that d8 would not simply add in an extra discard spell but swap it out for a Therapy. There was also some bias here as for the last year I have been running a Miser's Thoughtseize main and it whas been very strong, especially in the face of Thalias or Eidolons so much so that I have consider switching from three Therapy, two Duress one Thoughtseize main to three Therapy, one Duress and two Thoughtseize main.*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;parting&amp;#95;thoughts:&quot;&gt;Parting Thoughts:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;d8dk32's comments:&lt;br /&gt; I often talk to myself when I play online, but it's much more informative to talk to someone else who also knows your deck. Hopefully reading this and any future articles we publish will help people learning to play this deck, but I think this pair-playing process is a valuable learning tool and if you can find a willing partner would be an excellent way to learn on your own. Just as important as learning to build piles is learning how to make the plays in the early turns to reach the point where you get to build piles. Having someone to watch over your shoulder helps you play better by catching mistakes and providing a sounding board when the best line isn't clear. Doishy and I agreed on most things this time but discussing the reasoning behind our choices is helpful regardless.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doishy's comments:&lt;br /&gt; *I for one really enjoyed watching d8 play whilst we discussed decisions. What made me feel confidant was, barring some of the decision points above, we quite often agreed very quickly on what line to take with most being the correct one. In addition to the above we had a classic turn two &quot;Do we jam?&quot; vs what turned out to be an Esper Stoneblade/Delver variant. We both said yes and it was 100% correct given the circumstances. One thing that it made clear to me is how important it is having these very fluid conversations during gameplay. Although people at my local shops know me and my deck of choice none of them really &quot;know&quot; the deck to the point where I could properly discuss my card choices, play choices and similar.*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hopefully you enjoyed this first installment of Doomsday by Committee. We shall hopefully return with more of the super-secret-shadowy-Doomsday-cabal (TM) that might not exist with further discussion on other play points, opening hands, scenarios and occasional puzzles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<author>
d8dk32, Doishy
</author>
<enclosure>

</enclosure>
<pubDate>
Wed, 03 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
